<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Aleksandar Todorović (r3bl)</title>
 <link href="http://r3bl.github.io//atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="http://r3bl.github.io//"/>
 <updated>2015-01-25T15:01:00+01:00</updated>
 <id>http://r3bl.github.io/</id>
 <author>
   <name>Aleksandar Todorović</name>
   <email>aleksandar.todorovic@mail.ru</email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>Reasons Why GitHub is My Favorite Technology-Related Company</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/free%20culture/linux/2015/01/25/why-github-is-my-favorite-company/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-25T03:38:10+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/free%20culture/linux/2015/01/25/why-github-is-my-favorite-company</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this post I’m going to share with you a few reasons why I consider GitHub as my favorite technology-related company. If you still don’t know what GitHub is, you should continue reading this article because I’m going to share with you some of the most popular features GitHub has integrated in their service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/github_logo.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/github_logo.png?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;GitHub logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-github&quot;&gt;What is GitHub?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;GitHub is a web-based Git repository hosting service, which offers all of the distributed revision control and source code management (SCM) functionality of Git as well as adding its own features.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the definition I borrowed from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/GitHub&quot;&gt;GitHub Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt;. In short terms, it’s a place where every developer (or a student soon-to-be developer like me) can share their source code and their stories with the world. It’s a huge and highly respected collaboration platform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been used by every big technology company you can think of. Let me give you a few examples: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/google&quot;&gt;Google&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/twitter&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.mozilla.org/Github&quot;&gt;Mozilla&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://microsoft.github.io/&quot;&gt;Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://code.facebook.com/projects/&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://adobe.github.io/&quot;&gt;Adobe&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ibm.github.io/&quot;&gt;IBM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/yahoo&quot;&gt;Yahoo!&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/linkedin&quot;&gt;LinkedIn&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://netflix.github.io/&quot;&gt;Netflix&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/dropbox&quot;&gt;Dropbox&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/paypal&quot;&gt;PayPal&lt;/a&gt;. Still think GitHub doesn’t have a huge support? What if I told you that &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/WhiteHouse&quot;&gt;White House&lt;/a&gt; uses it too? I bet you didn’t know that some of these organizations even participate in the open source community at all!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why have they all chosen GitHub as a platform?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-great-place-to-store-your-code&quot;&gt;A Great Place to Store Your Code&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be honest, today, if you’re not hosting your source code on GitHub, your open source project does not exist. I have a lot of respect for other solutions such as &lt;a href=&quot;http://launchpad.net/&quot;&gt;Launchpad&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitbucket.org/&quot;&gt;BitBucket&lt;/a&gt;, but lets be honest, GitHub is the place to go if you need a place to share your source code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;huge-developer-community&quot;&gt;Huge Developer Community&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;There are 8.2M people collaborating right now across 19M repositories on GitHub. Developers from all around the world are building amazing things together. Their story is our story.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I borrowed this quote from GitHub’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/about&quot;&gt;press page&lt;/a&gt;. Over &lt;em&gt;eight million people&lt;/em&gt; is not a small number, and they’ve all chosen GitHub as their choice. Together, they’ve created around 19 million repositories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-as-a-replacement-for-linkedin&quot;&gt;GitHub as a Replacement for LinkedIn&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, I love LinkedIn and I’m using it myself for quite some time (you can find my LinkedIn profile &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.linkedin.com/in/aleksandartodorovic&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). But the truth is, you can post pretty much anything you want on LinkedIn and you can perfect your profile in any way you want. GitHub does not allow you to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;everything-you-publish-on-github-you-prove-it-right-away&quot;&gt;Everything you publish on GitHub, you prove it right away.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example, lets say that you posted on LinkedIn that you know how to program using C++. Your connections can endorse your skill and your employer can be sure that you know how to program using C++ if enough of your connections endorse it. But, if he visits your GitHub profile, he can see your C++ knowledge in action. He can read the code you’ve posted and based on the code, he can make sure that you’re a creative and a collaborative person, and that you have an experience in working with C++.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now don’t get me wrong, your GitHub is not a replacement for your resume and you should not think of it as a replacement for your resume. &lt;strong&gt;But&lt;/strong&gt;, it is a place where you can show your skills instead of talking about them. And there are some projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://osrc.dfm.io/&quot;&gt;Open Source Report Card&lt;/a&gt; that grabs your public GitHub data and represents them in a way that’s pretty similar to a resume (check out my Open Source Report Card &lt;a href=&quot;https://osrc.dfm.io/aleksandar-todorovic/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-pages&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let’s say that you want to build a website that represents you, your organization, your company, or anything else. You have a couple of options. You can buy your own domain and hosting service and build it from scratch. You can choose some freemium service like &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wix.com/&quot;&gt;Wix&lt;/a&gt;, where you will create a stunning website in minutes without any coding knowledge, but you will be limited to the features that service allows you to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, lets say that you want to have a full control over your site, &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; any limitations what so ever, &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; you showcase your website development and design skills in the process, all of that &lt;em&gt;completely free of charge&lt;/em&gt;. The solution? &lt;a href=&quot;https://pages.github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;! You can create your personal website, a website for your organization or a website for your project straight away. And it’s not really complicated to do that. Don’t believe me? Check out my &lt;a href=&quot;http://aleksandar-todorovic.github.io/&quot;&gt;online portfolio&lt;/a&gt;! It took me less than 15 minutes to create it using a template offered by GitHub, and I have a full control of that website, which explains how I managed to alter the design of the template called Hack by &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/bleikamp&quot;&gt;Ben Bleikamp&lt;/a&gt; (see how original template looks like &lt;a href=&quot;http://sundaykofax.github.io/baby-legs/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-training&quot;&gt;GitHub Training&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GitHub uses Git, which is a distributed revision control system designed and developed by Linus Torvalds for Linux kernel development back in 2005. It has become the most widely adopted version cotrol system for software development there is (&lt;a href=&quot;https://ianskerrett.wordpress.com/2014/06/23/eclipse-community-survey-2014-results/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, lets say that you don’t know how to work with Git, the same way I didn’t know how how to work with Git not too long ago. Problem? Heck no! All resources for working with Git using GitHub as a platform are already provided for you by GitHub itself! GitHub offers you free resources (or training kits as they call them) &lt;a href=&quot;https://training.github.com/kit/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and you also have a few free online courses available &lt;a href=&quot;https://training.github.com/classes/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Whatever learning option you choose to use out of those provided, you’ll see that your materials are divided in three difficulties: beginner/foundations, intermediate or advanced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-gists&quot;&gt;GitHub Gists&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the newest addition to the GitHub services. It’s a place where you’re able to share your text or a part of your code publicly (which means that your gist will be searchable by a search engine and viewed from your profile) or privately (which means that only people you choose are going to be able to view it, and you share Gists with them by simply copying a link).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;atom-text-editor&quot;&gt;Atom Text Editor&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After I found out about &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt;, I fell in love with GitHub all over again. Atom is a hackable text editor for the 21st Century (as advertised by GitHub).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, a hackable text editor, what does that even mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That means that you can hack every single thing inside of that text editor. Don’t know how? Not to worry, there are thousands of packages &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/packages&quot;&gt;already available&lt;/a&gt;, all of them hosted on GitHub and offered free of charge. Don’t like the design of the editor? Pick your favorite flavor of Atom out of thousands of them available &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/themes&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. You can customize your installation to be anything from a simple text editor to a full IDE (short for Integrated Development Environment). Heck, you can even write your publications, your blog posts or your books in it. In fact, I even used it to write the post you’re currently reading (see the picture below) in the same way I’m using it to write every single post on &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/screenshot-from-2015-01-25-024501.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/screenshot-from-2015-01-25-024501.png?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;Picture of how I wrote this post&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-student-developer-pack&quot;&gt;GitHub Student Developer Pack&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I recently discovered. A few days ago, I got a letter from my collage professor stating that as a student, I’m eligible to get a &lt;a href=&quot;https://education.github.com/pack&quot;&gt;GitHub Student Developer Pack&lt;/a&gt;, which offers me over 15 free and paid development tools from GitHub and its partners at a huge discount. Now, I should point out that I’m still in the verification process at the time this article is published. This process could last for weeks! But, I should also point out that a guy called Alex Fernandez from GitHub staff has personally apologized to me for that. The reason why this process lasts for so long is because they have to review each request manually, which does take quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/github-mark-64px.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/github-mark-64px.png&quot; alt=&quot;GitHub-Mark-64px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-has-an-amazing-support&quot;&gt;GitHub Has an Amazing Support&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m a developer. I use a lot of stable and unstable software and services on a daily basis and it is important to me to get the support as fast as possible. I had an issue with a certain GitHub feature so I decided to contact &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/contact&quot;&gt;GitHub support&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve got an email response in like 20 minutes, and they’ve been very helpful in the process. They’ve managed to explain to me why I had this issue and what I had to do to resolve it. I have to give them a straight 10/10 for their support.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-if-you-are-a-developer-is-there-a-reason-not-to-use-github&quot;&gt;So, if you are a developer, is there a reason &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; to use GitHub?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I don’t think there is. If you’re developing a proprietary software, there are plenty of reasons why you should not post the source code of your application on GitHub. But, that should not stop you from working on open source software in your free time. By doing so, it will benefit you (once you start looking for a new job), it will benefit the developers behind a project that you’ve decided to be a part of, and it will benefit every single user of that open source project. GitHub offers you a wide variety of opportunities and you should take advantage of them!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>My Manifesto</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/free%20culture/human%20hacking/2015/01/24/manifesto/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-24T23:46:19+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/free%20culture/human%20hacking/2015/01/24/manifesto</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Across my Reddit feed, I came up with this great article titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wiseism.com/write-personal-manifesto/&quot;&gt;Why You Should Write a Personal Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;, published by &lt;a href=&quot;http://wiseism.com/&quot;&gt;Wiseism&lt;/a&gt;. I feel like this is a great way to keep yourself motivated, so I’ve decided to do just that: to write down my own manifesto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m pretty confident that this manifesto really represents who I truly am, so I’ve decided to share it with you guys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of the post, there’s a picture with the manifesto that I made because I wanted to use it as my wallpaper. From time to time, I really enjoy reading &lt;a href=&quot;http://phrack.org/issues/7/3.html&quot;&gt;Hacker’s Manifesto&lt;/a&gt;, and I made this Manifesto to replace that occasional reading with something I wrote myself. This Manifesto is not new, it’s saved on my computer for a long time now and I had a different reason to write it. After reading this article, I’ve just rearranged it a little to look more “manifestish” (whatever that means).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&amp;gt; 
&amp;gt; # My Manifesto
&amp;gt; 
&amp;gt; 
I'm not like most of you.

I do not have emotions. I don't feel the same way as most people feel. I don't get hurt easily. I don't believe I'm going to go to hell if I do something. I don't believe I should be forbidden to do something I would like to do.

I'm not a role model of any kind and I'm not trying to be a role model to anyone. I've tried most of the things people consider bad. I don't think that anyone could help me if I don't want to help myself. I don't believe anyone will be by my side until death do as apart. I realize I'm on my own in this world and that's the way I like to live my life.

When I meet someone, all I see is a game. A game that I can win or loose. I don't get attached to people, all I see is a way to exploit them. A way to manipulate them to get what I want. And you know what I want? I want to be happy. And I am just that.

You wanna know why? Because I have something that most of the people surrounding me do not have. I have my mind and I know how to use it. I know how to make the best out of any situation and I'm perfectly happy in every situation I can possibly run into. I'm not saying I'm any more intelligent that you. I'm not saying that I think of myself as some higher species than most of the people. I'm not saying I've read more books than you. I'm just saying that I know how to be happy. I know how to feel alive...&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PNG version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/manifesto.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2015/01/manifesto.png?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;manifesto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The font used in the picture is my new favorite font called Ubuntu Mono. If you like the design used in this picture, you should thank &lt;a href=&quot;tombr.de&quot;&gt;Tom Brewe&lt;/a&gt; (GitHub username: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nylki&quot;&gt;nylki&lt;/a&gt;) for creating this awesome syntax theme for &lt;a href=&quot;http://atom.io/&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/nylki/pen-paper-coffee-syntax&quot;&gt;pen-paper-coffee-syntax&lt;/a&gt;. The wallpaper is basically a screenshot of the text (using that syntax theme and Ubuntu Mono font) slightly edited using GIMP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also thinking about creating a dark version of the wallpaper. If I decide to make it, I will update this post immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Kako mladi u mom okruženju koriste društvene mreže?</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/no%20hate%20speech%20online/2015/01/18/kako-mladi-koriste-drustvene-mreze/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-18T22:11:11+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/no%20hate%20speech%20online/2015/01/18/kako-mladi-koriste-drustvene-mreze</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;httpwwwcognitivebrandscomcreativeintelligencewp-contentuploads201408socialnetworksdepositphotos13876565xs-1jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://www.cognitivebrands.com/CreativeIntelligence/wp-content/uploads/2014/08/SocialNetworksDepositphotos_13876565_xs-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;uvod&quot;&gt;Uvod&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U ovom tekstu neću da pričam o statistici. U koliko vas zanimaju statistike o tome koliko se koja društvena mreža koristi, vrlo lako ćete pronaći sve potrebne podatke na internetu. U ovom tekstu ću da objasnim kako mladi u mojoj lokalnoj zajednici koriste koju društvenu mrežu, gledajući prvenstveno svoje vlastito iskustvo i iskustvo mojih prijatelja (onih van društvenih mreža).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ta-smatram-pod-pojmom-mladi&quot;&gt;Šta smatram pod pojmom mladi?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pod pojmom mladi u ovom tekstu smatram osobe između 16 i 20 godina. Dakle osobe stare da bi se nazivale tinejdžerima, ali premlade da bi se shvatile ozbiljno u svijetu odraslih osoba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;facebook&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sve više se primjeti da Facebook gubi moć među mojim prijateljima i poznanicima. Većina ga koristi samo zbog &lt;em&gt;chat&lt;/em&gt; opcije, koja je mnogo zastupljenija od bilo koje druge IM opcije. Primjeti se da sve manje ljudi objavljuje statuse. Objave se većinom svode na postavljanje novih fotografija, koje u većini slučajeva budu dijeljene sa Instagrama. Takođe se primjeti i da sve manje ljudi iz ove populacije zapravo čita početnu stranicu, te su korisnici sada većinom fokusirani na Facebook grupe, prvenstveno zbog toga što tu nema filtriranja vijesti. Korisnici sve više odustaju od objavljivanja sadržaja baš zbog tih algoritama. Vrlo je teško da će neki vaš &lt;em&gt;post&lt;/em&gt; postati popularan ako ništa prije toga niste objavili u posljednjih mjesec dana. Potrebna je predanost i aktivnost da bi bili čitani. Zbog toga je većina mojih prijatelja počela da traži alternativne metode da bi bili čitani.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koristi ga oko 95% osoba koje poznajem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;twitter&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter je vrlo specijalna društvena mreža na našim prostorima. Nema ogroman broj korisnika među nama, međutim oni koji ga koriste, to rade u ogromnim količinama. Provođenje nekoliko sati bez prestanka čitajući “lajnu” i postavljajući tvitove je postala sasvim normalna stvar. Uopšteno, ljudi ga koriste kao neku vrstu dnevnika, sa određenom dozom želje za pažnjom i sticanja “uticajnosti”, slike su rijetkost, a većina ljudi koje poznajem ne koriste svoj pravi identitet prilikom korišćenja ove društvene mreže, te se zbog tih razloga mnogo češće susrećemo sa govorima mržnje nego na ostalim društvenim mrežama. Govori mržnje su prvenstveno fokusirani protiv pojedinaca koji ne koriste ovu društvenu mrežu. Međutim, ukoliko mislite da bi se uklanjanjem anonimnosti riješio govor mržnje, želim da vas podsjetim da &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/12/04/anonimnost-nije-rjesenje/&quot;&gt;uklanjanje anonimnosti nije rješenje&lt;/a&gt; za borbu protiv govora mržnje. Evidentno je i da je novoj osobi koja se pridruži ovoj mreži potrebna ogromna količina truda da bi bila prihvaćena od strane “iskusnijih” tviteraša.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koristi ga oko 50% osoba koje poznajem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tumblr&quot;&gt;Tumblr&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nešto između vlastitog bloga i Twitter profila je upravo Tumblr. Mjesto gdje osobe koje poznajem pronalaze inspiraciju, maštaju o nekom idealnom životu, te objavljuju uopšteno slike stvari koje im se sviđaju. Početna na Tumblr-u je obično prepuna slika, a kao ultimativni razlog zašto se toliki broj mojih prijatelja i poznanika okreće upravo ovoj društevnoj mreži ispred vođenja vlastitog bloga smatram lakoću vođenja bloga preko repostovanja stvari koje nam se sviđaju.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koristi ga oko 20% osoba koje poznajem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;instagram&quot;&gt;Instagram&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ne koristim ovu društvenu mrežu i, da budem iskren, ne razumijem u potpunosti poentu ove društvene mreže, međutim sasvim je očigledno da ovaj servis sve veći broj mojih Facebook prijatelja koristi kao način za dijeljenje fotografija na Facebook-u.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koristi ga oko 40% osoba koje poznajem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;gag&quot;&gt;9gag&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iako cilj ovog sajta nije da postane društvena mreža, evidentno je da uvođenjem 9gag profila i količinom komentara ispod svakog viralnog posta 9gag ide prema tom pravcu. Posjetioci 9gag-a se u velikoj mjeri drže zajedno i vrlo je lako novoj osobi da postane dio te zajednice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Koristi ga oko 20% osoba koje poznajem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reddit&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Poznajem još samo dvije osobe koje su aktivne na Reddit-u. Iako vrlo nepopularan među osobama koje poznajem, evidentno je da ga osobe koje ga koriste koriste u vrlo velikoj mjeri. Smatra se vrlo “zrelom” socijalnom mrežom, sa mnogo konstruktivnih i objektivnih rasprava o trenutno aktuelnim temama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;vlastiti-blogovi&quot;&gt;Vlastiti blogovi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ova metoda društvene pripadnosti je vrlo rijetka među mojim poznanicima. Pored mene, poznajem još samo dvije osobe koje vode svoj blog, međutim, za razliku od mene, te dvije osobe svoj blog vode anonimno, bez želje da ih čitaju ljudi ih poznaju van društvenih mreža.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;zakljuak&quot;&gt;Zaključak&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smatram da je za uspijeh neke društvene mreže vrlo važno uzeti u obzir način na koji bi ga potencijali korisnici koristili. Iako je bitno ponuditi nešto novo korisnicima, vrlo je evidentno i da korisnici neće prihvatiti tu društvenu mrežu ukoliko je ne počne koristiti određena doza poznanika.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Takođe, evidentno je i da društvene mreže koje su bazirane na to da budu ultimativno rješenje za vođenje društvenog života počinju da propadaju, što bih naveo kao razlog sve većeg nezadovoljstva korišćenjem Facebook-a i potpunoj propasti Google+-a kao društvene mreže. Moglo bi se reći da moji poznanici pri korišćenju društvenih mreža prate Linux filozofiju, tako što traže jedan servis preko kojeg će da rade tačno određeni zadatak umjesto da koriste ultimativna društvena rješenja.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Napomena&lt;/strong&gt;: Tekst je napisan po uzori na &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/backchannel/a-teenagers-view-on-social-media-1df945c09ac6&quot;&gt;ovaj tekst&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Best (Linux) Programs and Services I've Started Using in 2014.</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/2015/01/10/best-linux-programs-and-services-in-2014/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-10T18:19:41+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/2015/01/10/best-linux-programs-and-services-in-2014</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this post, I’m going to share with you a couple of programs / web services / apps that I’ve started using regularly in 2014. I’ve discovered some of them in 2013, but in 2014 I really started to use them on a regular basis. I hope that you will find something for yourself in my list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;best-operating-system-elementary-os-freyahttpelementaryosorg&quot;&gt;Best operating system: &lt;a href=&quot;http://elementaryos.org/&quot;&gt;elementary OS Freya&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using elementary OS since 2013. But it definitely became my primary operating system in 2014. I haven’t used Windows in months now and I’m not missing anything. Plus, It’s a real joy participating in the development since the release of Beta 1 version. I’m also &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/11/elementary-os-bosnian-language/&quot;&gt;translating elementary OS to Bosnian language&lt;/a&gt; in my free time. Too bad I haven’t finished my job by the end of 2014, but I think that the translation is pretty much usable by now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;best-text-editor-atomhttpsatomio&quot;&gt;Best text editor: &lt;a href=&quot;https://atom.io/&quot;&gt;Atom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a hackable text editor for the 21st century, as advertised by worldly-known &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve been using it for a couple of months and loving every single aspect of it. In fact, I’m writing this and every single other article in it using Markdown as a styling language before posting them to Wordpress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;best-productivity-apps-todotxthttptodotxtcom-gitithttpgititnet-and-rescuetimehttprescuetimecom&quot;&gt;Best productivity apps: &lt;a href=&quot;http://todotxt.com/&quot;&gt;Todo.txt&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://gitit.net/&quot;&gt;Gitit&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://rescuetime.com/&quot;&gt;RescueTime&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been using &lt;a href=&quot;http://evernote.com/&quot;&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt; for a couple of months, but the clunky interface of the desktop version for Windows and the fact that there is no official Linux client really started to annoy me big time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I’ve started looking for the alternatives and Todo.txt in a combination with Gitit looks like a perfect alternative to me. So, what I’ve started doing is writing my notes inside a wiki that I’m running on my local machine (using Gitit as a platform).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m using Todo.txt as my to-do list natively in Linux using &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mNantern/QTodoTxt&quot;&gt;QTodoTxt&lt;/a&gt; and so far it works great! Been using it for a couple of months now and I see no reason why I won’t be using it throughout 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;RescueTime is not really a productivity app. It’s more of a way to see how productive you are really. With the native application running in the background, I can see how much of my time has been spent doing something productive. Native Linux client and Firefox add-on are a perfect combination for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;best-tools-for-communication-pidginhttppidginim-my-bloghttpsaleksandartodorovicwordpresscom-and-twitterhttpstwittercomr3bl&quot;&gt;Best tools for communication: &lt;a href=&quot;http://pidgin.im/&quot;&gt;Pidgin&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;my blog&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/r3bl_&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m really loving the way Pidgin is integrated in my operating system. I’ve been using it since 2013, but now I’m using it exclusively to chat with my Facebook friends. In fact, I’m opening Facebook no more than once a day now, which means that most of my time is spent doing something a little bit more productive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really found myself in the management of this blog. I’m enjoying every second of writing stuff for my audience and I’m pretty satisfied with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2015/01/01/blog-stats-2014/&quot;&gt;support I’m getting from you guys&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Twitter has been my primary social network since the end of the 2013. But, in 2014, I’ve started running two Twitter profiles, one personal, and one for my business communications. I’ve managed to bond with some awesome people and learn a lot by reading articles other people are suggesting to me through their Twitter feed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;best-cloud-service-megahttpsmegaconz&quot;&gt;Best cloud service: &lt;a href=&quot;https://mega.co.nz/&quot;&gt;MEGA&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I have 1 TB of space on &lt;a href=&quot;http://onedrive.live.com/&quot;&gt;OneDrive&lt;/a&gt; and one more TB of space in &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.mail.ru/&quot;&gt;Mail.Ru Cloud&lt;/a&gt;, I have to select MEGA as my favourite for 2014. Unlike Mail.Ru Cloud and OneDrive it has a perfectly integrated Linux client and 50 GB of space is enough to satisfy my needs for now, although I’m planning to switch to some premium plan in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;best-reading-services-kindlehttpsreadamazoncom-and-digghttpdiggcom&quot;&gt;Best reading services: &lt;a href=&quot;https://read.amazon.com/&quot;&gt;Kindle&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://digg.com/&quot;&gt;Digg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s been a while since I’ve discovered Kindle ebook readers. I’m still thinking about whether should I buy one or not. In the meantime, I’m really enjoying reading books through the online interface of the Kindle reader. I have over 150 books in my library now thanks to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/freeebooks&quot;&gt;Free eBooks subreddit&lt;/a&gt; and a simple &lt;a href=&quot;https://ifttt.com/myrecipes/personal/17091741&quot;&gt;IFTTT recipe&lt;/a&gt; which sends me the daily digest of new posts. I haven’t payed a dime for any of the books in it and I have books that are probably worth more than $1,000 dollars by now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Digg is the perfect way for me to stay in touch with the latest news from my favourite blogs (such as those in my blogroll in the sidebar).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;best-multimedia-services-popcorn-timehttppopcorntimeio-spotifyhttpswwwspotifycomus-and-clementinehttpswwwclementine-playerorg&quot;&gt;Best multimedia services: &lt;a href=&quot;http://popcorntime.io/&quot;&gt;Popcorn Time&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spotify.com/us/&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.clementine-player.org/&quot;&gt;Clementine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though I’m not a huge fan of pirating (I’m all about open source software and creative commons), the fact &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; that I live in a country where most of the movies and TV shows are not available. Popcorn Time really helps me to be in touch with my favourite TV shows and I’m loving the simplicity and the design of the application itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m from Bosnia &amp;amp; Herzegovina, a country with &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; music streaming service &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt;. That’s why I’ve had to wake the hacker inside of me and found a solution to run Spotify as my choice. Basically, I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.vpnbook.com/freevpn&quot;&gt;OpenVPN&lt;/a&gt; once every 15 days to log into my Spotify account and then I enter a “vacation mode”, which enables me to run Spotify for the next 15 days. And Spotify does have a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spotify.com/int/download/other/&quot;&gt;Spotify for Linux Preview&lt;/a&gt; client which, although a bit unstable, does the job perfectly for me so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now, why am I including Clementine in this list? Well, it’s because of the Internet streaming option. I’m a big &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.di.fm/&quot;&gt;Digitally Imported&lt;/a&gt; fan for quite some time and recently I’ve started listening to &lt;a href=&quot;http://somafm.com/&quot;&gt;SomaFM&lt;/a&gt; in the background while I’m doing something productive. I’ve chosen Clementine because it’s the perfect &lt;em&gt;out-of-the-box&lt;/em&gt; solution for streaming those two services. In fact, I’m listening to my favourite Digitally Imported station called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.di.fm/bassnjackinhouse&quot;&gt;Bass &amp;amp; Jackin’ House&lt;/a&gt; right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;games-2048httpgabrielecirulligithubio2048-0h-h1http0hh1com-and-south-park-the-stick-of-truthhttpsenwikipediaorgwikisouthparkthestickoftruth&quot;&gt;Games: &lt;a href=&quot;http://gabrielecirulli.github.io/2048/&quot;&gt;2048&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://0hh1.com/&quot;&gt;0h H1&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/South_Park:_The_Stick_of_Truth&quot;&gt;South Park: The Stick of Truth&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have any desire to play any complicated graphical game anymore. I’ve started to be a fan of logical games such as 2048 and Oh H1. The reason why I’m loving these two games is because they’re pretty simple to play, and the fact is that I’m not playing them for hours like I’ve used to play games like &lt;a href=&quot;http://worldoftanks.eu/&quot;&gt;World of Tanks&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.2k.com/games/nba-2k15&quot;&gt;NBA by 2k Sports&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From time to time, everyone needs a good amount of laugh. That’s why I really enjoyed playing South Park video game. Simple graphical interface + a good amount of humour is the winning combination in my case. I really wish that there’s a Linux version of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might also enjoy reading the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/12/28/top-quotes-2014/&quot;&gt;Top Motivational Quotes I’ve Discovered in 2014&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Advice for living in this world (by Quinn Norton)</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///free%20culture/2015/01/09/advice-for-living-in-this-world/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-09T19:12:06+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//free%20culture/2015/01/09/advice-for-living-in-this-world</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wow, this is the first time (although I can’t guarantee you that it will be the last) that I’m going to share with you a story that was &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; written by myself. And there’s an excellent reason for that. I don’t think that I’ve read a single story (or an article if you please) that had so much influence on me about today’s technology. It was written by &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quinn_Norton&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quinn Norton&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; and published in a book called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shareconference.net/en/news/share-book&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share This Book (2012)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.shareconference.net/en&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Share Foundation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Please, read it thoroughly. I promise you that you &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be amazed by this astonishing piece of writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&amp;gt; 
&amp;gt; ## **Advice for Living in this World**
&amp;gt; 
&amp;gt; 
Every day is stranger than the last one.

Each of us has a point where we fall short, where we can’t go on at this mad pace. We ride the wave as long as we can until we start to drown in time and change, and nothing makes sense anymore. And then we fight back from that insanity. This is so common an experience, it’s practically a rite of passage in our new online lives.

Somewhere along the way our networks exceeded us. We spent 12,000 years carving civilization out of the wild, and at the very edge of
its most technical, most complex, most beautiful moment, it became wild again. Like a matryoshka doll of our human disasters, from within our safe, designed and managed world, we built forests of infinite darkness. In the spaces between our devices, we populated this new wild with the predatorial spirits we’d exterminated from the outer landscape. Once again we face disease, dark creatures, black magics, and the all-seeing eyes of evil gods, all in the worlds we’ve created between us, all embedded in our most logical and mathematical system.

Technological life is just becoming life, it takes the weird and violent paths of life. Our network is biologically complex, unpredictable, a state of nature. It’s obtaining the qualities of forests, seas, galaxies -- filled with unearthly beauty, the apprehension of which will pull the breath from your lungs. And like nature, it’s complex and messy and every story, every single one, ends in death.

We need the oldest human tools for this new landscape. This is an age of elemental magic, battling wizards, and capricious gods. To make sense of this world, the routers and servers need their own nymphs and dryads, cable lays need the Shinto river gods, and we need to see Coyote and Raven passing through the application layer, bickering and upsetting the world as they go, but eventually bringing us pieces of the sun.

These are the opening moments of a mythic age, a polytheistic age. The drab but reliable monotheism, the old man God, and the careful
and slow secular rationalism he engendered, then fought, kept order in the world for a long time. God and Secular Rationalism were both
cut from the same cloth, mostly by reasonable men with proper ways to go about things that made the world predictable, rational, reasonable, hierarchal. But they couldn’t run fast enough to catch us in the 21st century. We overwhelmed them with a trillion tiny imps, little daemon servants that spawned, made trouble, and died before an ant could so much as shake its legs. We can still hear the Old Man and Rationalism screaming in the ever receding distance behind us, and before us, a world of chaos and weird constructed and endlessly self constructing from their technological inventions.

Our laptops will live in the corners of our domiciles, and we will take them with us, like the ancestral Roman housegods. We will come to see programming as magical incantations: cantrips that make small things happen, or great and long rituals that can stop time or turn the world from light to dark. We increasingly live in fear of these magics, not understanding them, but knowing there are those few gifted and sinister humans who do.

And the stories we will have, of them, of us! In the coming years we are going to need many gods to make sense of this world. We will
write many new myths to teach our loved ones and keep them safe. With no chance of understanding it all, we will need superstitions to guide us through the forests of the net. We face the old magic of ghosts in our machines, the sympathetic magic of DNA samples, and the voodoo of control in true names. Any sufficiently advanced magic turns out to be indistinguishable from technology.

I encourage you to pick up one of the old religions, and an amulet against the evil eye-- perhaps TOR + one of those lovely mediterranean glass beads. Read the old myths, and consider how they might be useful, how they are, in fact, true now. Find out the basic sigils that folks use in dark woods, and carry talismans against things that prey on network travelers in the downcycle night. We have ways for times like these, we just haven’t used them in a while. These are the things we need to dust off, gods and myths are
how we manage unmanageable nature-- even if we supposedly built it. Without them, we are lost, outdated, clinging to old ways and being harvested by evil things that eat the slow and careful. Nature, even this strange network nature we’ve created, does not reduce, it does not compress, and like all free things, it is terribly dangerous.

Rationalism had its run, but it’s just not rational anymore.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Blog Stats for the Year 2014. (Happy 2015!)</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///2015/01/01/blog-stats-2014/"/>
   <updated>2015-01-01T01:13:20+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//2015/01/01/blog-stats-2014</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This blog is active since July the 12th (so almost a half of a year).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Number of views: 4,389&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Number of visitors: 2,616&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Number of posts: 53&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got most of my views from:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;search engines (973) (898 from Google)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Reddit (852)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Twitter (282)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Top countries:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;United States – 1,058 views&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Bosnia &amp;amp; Herzegovina – 824 views&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Serbia – 698 views&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other countries with over 100 views: United Kingdom (135), Canada (134), Croatia (132), Germany (118), and India (111).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Top 10 pages (with the number of views in brackets):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Home page/Archive (795)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Top Motivational Quotes I’ve Discovered in 2014 (666)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ko koga špijunira u političkom vrhu BiH? (2. dio) (465)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” - Hack no. 3: See Locked Profile Picture in Full Size (359)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get Office 365 licence for free! [A Little Contest] (299)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” - Hack no. 1: Check who’s your biggest “stalker” without leaving Facebook (208)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Through The Algorithm (2014) To a Free World (188)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Ko koga špijunira u političkom vrhu BiH? (185)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Papers We Love (152)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Material Design in Linux (120)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Number of followers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Wordpress followers: 10&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Twitter followers: 103&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those stats are nothing special but I’m really proud of them. Now I’m starting to get over 50 visitors on a daily basis (in the last 15 days). After I got a pretty decent amount of initial attention, I’ve decided that this blog is a perfect way for me to express myself. That’s why I’m going to take &lt;a href=&quot;https://dailypost.wordpress.com/2014/12/29/blogging-101-january-registration/&quot;&gt;Blogging 101&lt;/a&gt;, a free online course (starting January the 5th) offered by Wordpress to further my knowledge of running a blog. After all, I love learning new things, which is the main reason why I started this blog in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve got a huge (and I really mean &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt;) number of drafts prepared for 2015 so expect a new post at least two times a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goals for 2015:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over 30,000 views (7 times more than in 2014)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over 20,000 visitors (8 times more than in 2014)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Over 1,000 Twitter followers (10 times more than in 2014)&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Loving the support I’m getting from you guys and those numbers definitely suggest to me that I should keep posting. Thanks to every single one of you guys and a happy 2015!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Top Motivational Quotes I Discovered in 2014</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/2014/12/28/top-quotes-2014/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-28T01:30:10+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/2014/12/28/top-quotes-2014</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, everybody is sharing a list of something they came up with in the year behind them. I’m going to step it up a little. I present to you a very special list of mine. I represent to you the list of quotes that kept me motivated and inspired in 2014. This list is _very _special to me and I’ve decided to give it to you guys as a reward for reading my blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, here we go:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Latin: &lt;/strong&gt; Imperare sibi maximum imperium est. - To rule yourself is the ultimate power.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Duane Michals:&lt;/strong&gt;  Trust that little voice in your head that says “Wouldn’t it be interesting if…” And then do it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Friedrich Nietzsche:&lt;/strong&gt; In individuals, insanity is rare; but in groups, parties, nations, and epochs it is the rule.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joseph Brodsky:&lt;/strong&gt; There are worse crimes than burning books. One of them is not reading them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oscar Wilde:&lt;/strong&gt; Give a man mask and he’ll tell you the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jim Morrison: &lt;/strong&gt; There can’t be any large-scale revolution until there’s a personal revolution, on an individual level. It’s got to happen inside first.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Napoleon Hill: &lt;/strong&gt; Patience, persistence and perspiration make an unbeatable combination for success.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark Twain: &lt;/strong&gt; Never let your school interfere with your education.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mark Victor Hansen:&lt;/strong&gt;  Don’t wait until everything is just right. It will never be perfect. There will always be challenges, obstacles and less than perfect conditions. So what. Get started now. With each step you take, you will grow stronger and stronger, more and more skilled, more and more self-confident and more and more successful.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Michael Jordan:&lt;/strong&gt;  I can accept failure, everyone fails at something. But I can’t accept not trying.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Mae West:&lt;/strong&gt;  You only live once, but if you do it right, once is enough.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Frank Zappa:&lt;/strong&gt;  If you end up with a boring miserable life because you listened to your mom, your dad, your teacher, your priest, or some guy on television telling you how to do your shit, then you deserve it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Will Smith:&lt;/strong&gt; You don’t try to build a wall. You don’t set out to build a wall. You don’t say, “I’m gonna build the biggest baddest greatest wall, that’s ever been build,”, you don’t start there. You say, “I’m gonna lay this brick, as perfectly as a brick can be laid,” and you do that, every single day. And soon you have a wall.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m going to represent to you a list of quotes taken from the book called &lt;a href=&quot;http://stlcurator.com/henry-goldkamp-what-the-hell-stl/&quot;&gt;What The Hell is Saint Louis Thinking? (2014)&lt;/a&gt;. It’s a book written by the city itself. It’s written by hundreds of citizens of Saint Louis and there are some quite interesting quotes there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We all drive on, walk past each other, not really knowing who we are. We’re all just strangers passing in the street, never stopping or taking the time.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;There is no reason to simply exist. You need to exist for a reason. That reason can be silly to everyone but you. Hold it dear to your heart. Never forget it and never deny it for it is the reason to keep sucking oxygen.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;What you do in your life changes what someone else does in theirs, and that changes everything.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;We are all raindrops. We might seem small and insignificant but together we have the power of the world.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Fear keeps me from dreaming so I will not live my life in fear!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I’m going to share with you a song that kept me motivated in the 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LkCkCPfDmqQ&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy 2015. guys! Feel free to share some quote in the comments that influenced you the most in the year behind us!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might also want to check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2015/01/10/best-linux-programs-and-services-in-2014/&quot;&gt;Best (Linux) Programs and Services I’ve Started Using in 2014&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Every One of Us Changes the World in One Way or Another</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/free%20culture/2014/12/27/every-one-of-us-changes-the-world-in-one-way-or-another/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-27T15:08:46+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/free%20culture/2014/12/27/every-one-of-us-changes-the-world-in-one-way-or-another</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;blockquote&gt;We are all raindrops. We might seem small and insignificant, but together we have the power of the world.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a quote by an unknown author from a book called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://stlcurator.com/henry-goldkamp-what-the-hell-stl/&quot;&gt;What The Hell is Saint Louis Thinking? (2014)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. It’s an excellent book and I suggest you to read it. Oh, and did I mention that it’s free?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I really think that this quote really covers it all. We all shape the world somehow. Maybe we did something important today, and maybe we didn’t. But even if we didn’t, we might have influenced the world in some indirect way, by bothering someone with our problems and taking their time that might have been spent doing something that might influence the world in a much larger way, or by giving some kind of a motivation to someone which will help him to do something significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep hearing that “&lt;em&gt;I want to change the world&lt;/em&gt;” cliché and frankly, I’m sick of it. It’s not about changing the world, changing the world is something that you do &lt;em&gt;while you’re thinking about changing the world&lt;/em&gt;. It’s about changing the world &lt;em&gt;as much as you can&lt;/em&gt;. It’s about broadening your change to a much higher spectrum than the average person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every action that we take our ancestors took helped to the design the world we live in today. And we need to be quite careful because actions we do &lt;em&gt;now&lt;/em&gt; will design the future for our future generations. And every action counts, be it a coffee with someone, writing this, programming something, going to a conference, spending the night drinking, or anything in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to end this with one more quote. I can’t remember where I read it and searching for it on the Internet did not gave me any usable result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;A man has two deaths. The first time when he physically dies, and the second time when his name is mentioned for the last time.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Run Your Own Copy of Pirate Bay Now!</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///free%20culture/projects/2014/12/19/run-your-own-copy-of-pirate-bay-now/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-19T17:04:56+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//free%20culture/projects/2014/12/19/run-your-own-copy-of-pirate-bay-now</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/openbaylogo.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/openbaylogo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Open Bay logo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;OK, so, as you probably already know, the official Pirate Bay was shut down 10 days ago. There are plenty of articles already covering this subject. I already stated &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/12/14/is-it-time-for-the-pirate-bay-to-disappear-for-good/&quot;&gt;my opinion on Pirate Bay disappearing for good&lt;/a&gt;, where &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.brokep.com/2014/12/09/the-pirate-bay-down-forever/&quot;&gt;I agreed with Peter Sunde&lt;/a&gt; (co-founder and ex-spokesperson of the Pirate Bay).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are already some non-legit Pirate Bay clones &lt;a href=&quot;http://torrentfreak.com/fake-pirate-bay-lies-to-press-and-fakes-user-uploads-141215/&quot;&gt;like this one&lt;/a&gt;, the Pirate Bay &lt;a href=&quot;http://torrentfreak.com/the-pirate-bay-has-not-been-resurrected-yet-141210/&quot;&gt;has not been ressurrected - yet&lt;/a&gt;, the Pirate Bay crew itself &lt;a href=&quot;http://torrentfreak.com/pirate-bay-crew-responds-to-the-raid-copies-and-the-future-141215/&quot;&gt;does not know&lt;/a&gt; will the Pirate Bay come online or not, and researchers &lt;a href=&quot;http://torrentfreak.com/bittorrent-anonymous-and-impossible-to-shut-down-141218/&quot;&gt;are currently working on&lt;/a&gt; making BitTorrent anonymous and impossible to shut down. It’s pretty obvious that the copyright industry &lt;a href=&quot;http://torrentfreak.com/how-to-learn-absolutely-nothing-in-fifteen-years-by-the-copyright-industry-141214/&quot;&gt;has learned absolutely nothing&lt;/a&gt; in the least fifteen years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The system now is messed up, but that &lt;a href=&quot;http://torrentfreak.com/pirate-bay-shutdown-doesnt-stop-people-sharing-141216/&quot;&gt;hasn’t stopped people from sharing&lt;/a&gt; using their favorite technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;presenting-open-bay&quot;&gt;Presenting: Open Bay&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Out of all those alternatives that came online after the raid, one really stands out and it’s called &lt;a href=&quot;https://oldpiratebay.org/&quot;&gt;Old Pirate Bay&lt;/a&gt;. So, why &lt;em&gt;exactly&lt;/em&gt; did it stand out? Well, the whole point is that this copy is from a reputable source (&lt;a href=&quot;http://isohunt.to/&quot;&gt;isoHunt&lt;/a&gt;). Now, isoHunt is taking one step further by doing something Pirate Bay should have done a long time ago: they released the source code of Old Pirate Bay to the public and called it &lt;a href=&quot;http://openbay.isohunt.to/&quot;&gt;The Open Bay&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find all of the source code in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/isohuntto/openbay/&quot;&gt;GitHub repository&lt;/a&gt;. You can host your own version of the Pirate Bay on your private server. You can even create your local torrent search engine, something I will try to do (if I manage to do that, there will be a tutorial on my blog on how to do that).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of doing this is simple: making pirates impossible to stop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;issues&quot;&gt;Issues&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this brigs up so many issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How will we know what site is legit?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How will we update our torrent database?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;How will we know what site does have an updated version of the torrent database?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These issues are yet to be resolved. If you do have some suggestions, leave them in the comments bellow or &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/isohuntto/openbay/issues/new&quot;&gt;create an issue&lt;/a&gt; on the repository itself. Lets make pirating impossible to stop together!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Ljudi vam dosađuju pitanjima tipa kako postati haker? Evo rješenja</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/free%20culture/human%20hacking/linux/projects/2014/12/17/dosta-kako-postati-haker-pitanja/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-17T17:38:49+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/free%20culture/human%20hacking/linux/projects/2014/12/17/dosta-kako-postati-haker-pitanja</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;uvod&quot;&gt;Uvod&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Svako od nas se bar u jednom trenutku života zamislio kakav je osjećaj biti haker? Možda ste i pokušali da istražite malo tu temu, a nemate dovoljno dobro znanje engleskog jezika da bi pratili engleske tutorijale? Možda imate druga koji je vidio da koristite Linux i odma je pomislio da ste haker? Možda vodite blog post i dobijate konstanta pitanja tipa “Kako da hakujem Fejsbuk od svoje bivše”?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukoliko spadate u bilo koju od ovih skupina, velike su šanse da nemate baš dovoljno živaca, motivacije i želje da objašnjavate svakome šta znači ovaj pojam. Zbog toga sam odlučio da sve postove domaćih autora sakupim na jedno mjesto, tako da od sada kada god dobijete slično pitanje možete sagovorniku poslati jedan link i završiti sa diskusijom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;predstavljam-vam-kako-postati-hakerhttpsgithubcomaleksandar-todorovickako-postati-haker-repozitorij&quot;&gt;Predstavljam vam &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aleksandar-todorovic/kako-postati-haker&quot;&gt;kako-postati-haker&lt;/a&gt; repozitorij&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ideja ovog repozitorija jeste da se na jednom mjestu objave linkovi prema svim tekstovima domaćih autora (bili oni na “našem” jeziku ili na engleskom) na ovu temu, da se poređaju smisleno i pravilno grupišu. Na ovaj način se kreira jedinstvena lista tekstova preko koje nove osobe mogu da nauče nešto više o ovom pojmu, te se na taj način skida teret sa nas ostalih da prelazimo iste teme više puta i oslobađa nam se vrijeme da radimo neke bitnije stvari (tipa rekompajliranje kernela).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Repozitorij sadrži samo linkove prema teksovima. Na taj način piscima nije uskraćen broj posjeta na njihovim web stranicama. Pored svakog teksta se nalazi i naziv autora, te link prema njegovoj službenoj web stranici.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;budui-planovi&quot;&gt;Budući planovi&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trenutno imam samo jedan plan za budućnost ovog projekta, a taj plan jeste da listu postavim na sopstveni host umjesto da se listi pristupa GitHub repozotorij. Pošto trenutno nemam iznajmljen vlastiti host, kreiraću GitHub stranicu za projekat i predstaviti ga tamo u međuvremenu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kako-doprinijeti-projektu&quot;&gt;Kako doprinijeti projektu?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doprinijeti projektu možete na više načina. Prvi način svakako jeste da pronađete tekstove na ovu temu i dodate ih na listu (ukoliko ne znate kako, jednostavno me &lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#097;&amp;#108;&amp;#101;&amp;#107;&amp;#115;&amp;#097;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#046;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#111;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#099;&amp;#064;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#046;&amp;#114;&amp;#117;&quot;&gt;kontaktirajte&lt;/a&gt; i ja ću to odraditi umjesto vas). Možete da dijelite ovaj repozitorij ili pišete o njemu pa da na taj način više ljudi sazna za njega. Možete da pišete originalan sadržaj na ovu temu da popunite praznine. Možete da mi pomognete da napravim web stranicu projekta učestvovanjem u izradi HTML verzije stranice ili dijeljenjem svojih hosting resursa za ovu svrhu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;tekstovi-koji-nee-biti-primljeni&quot;&gt;Tekstovi koji neće biti primljeni&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dozvoljeni su samo tekstovi prema kojima čitaoc nije dužan da se registruje na neki sajt da bi ih pročitao.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Some Basic Facebook "Hacks" - Hack no. 4: DDoS a Website By Using Facebook</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///cyber%20security/projects/2014/12/15/facebook-hack-no4/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-15T04:56:53+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//cyber%20security/projects/2014/12/15/facebook-hack-no4</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, today I’m going to share with you a trick to DDoS a certain website by using Facebook’s notes feature. The process, although pretty simple, is a bit more complicated than previous posts I wrote in this series.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what do you need to do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, first of all, you go to the target’s website and create a list with unique photos posted on that website. You put them in appropriate HTML tag like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;img src=”http://targetname/file?r=1” /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;img src=”http://targetname/file?r=2” /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;lt;img src=”http://targetname/file?r=1000” /&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next thing you need to do is to write a note on &lt;a href=&quot;http://m.facebook.com/&quot;&gt;m.facebook.com&lt;/a&gt; (it’s a mobile version of Facebook).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, you need to duplicate that note a couple of times with one &lt;em&gt;or&lt;/em&gt; several other Facebook accounts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you’ve done that, all you need to do is to open that notes at the same time and watch the site go down. This process will generate thousands of HTTP requests in a couple of seconds to the target site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might want to check out previous posts in the series:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/13/facebook-hack-no1/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 1: Check who’s your biggest “stalker” without leaving Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/13/facebook-hack-no2/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 2: Find out who’s calling you on your phone by using Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/20/facebook-hack-no3/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 3: See Locked Profile Picture in Full Size&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Is It Time For The Pirate Bay to Disappear For Good?</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///free%20culture/politics/2014/12/14/is-it-time-for-the-pirate-bay-to-disappear-for-good/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-14T18:54:27+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//free%20culture/politics/2014/12/14/is-it-time-for-the-pirate-bay-to-disappear-for-good</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/selection_002.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/selection_002.png&quot; alt=&quot;Selection_002&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, a few days ago, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Pirate_Bay&quot;&gt;The Pirate Bay&lt;/a&gt; was raided. The site itself is still not online and we have no indications whether or not it &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; come back online. There’s a lot of fake sites that advertise themselves as The Pirate Bay, but are basically of no use (users can’t upload new torrents, the database of torrents is either too old or don’t work at all).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I myself can’t figure out do I want The Pirate Bay to stay down or to come back online. So, why am I saying that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, first of all, the fact is that The Pirate Bay had a huge influence in making the world what it is today (I will probably cover that topic in some future blog post). But, lets be honest, the design of the website is way too old, the code behind the website is pretty outdated too, and there’s nothing new going on on the site itself for quite some time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we look at those flaws, we can basically say that the site itself got ran over by time. But don’t get me wrong, The Pirate Bay itself did an excellent job at what it was supposed to do. It had the biggest torrent collection available on the Internet, it had the biggest reputation amongst all other peer-to-peer (P2P) services, and it is one of the top 100 visited websites at the moment (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.alexa.com/siteinfo/thepiratebay.se&quot;&gt;according to Alexa&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, maybe it’s time for something new? &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Peter_Sunde&quot;&gt;Peter Sunde&lt;/a&gt;, co-founder and ex-spokesperson of The Pirate Bay definitely &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.brokep.com/2014/12/09/the-pirate-bay-down-forever/&quot;&gt;agrees with me&lt;/a&gt; on that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;**Peter Sunde:** It feels good that it might have closed down forever, just a real shame the way it did that. A planned retirement would have given the community time and a way to kick off something new, something better, something faster, something more reliable and with no chance of corrupting itself. Something that had a soul and could retain it.&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is the &lt;a href=&quot;http://oldpiratebay.org/&quot;&gt;Old Pirate Bay&lt;/a&gt; exactly what we’re looking for? Old Pirate Bay is a search engine provided by &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IsoHunt&quot;&gt;Iso&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IsoHunt&quot;&gt;hunt&lt;/a&gt;, one of the biggest competitors to The Pirate Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design of the site feels like it’s an upgraded version of The Pirate Bay. The site works perfectly and the workflow of the site is pretty much the same as in The Pirate Bay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to agree with Peter, it is time for The Pirate Bay to shutdown completely, and it is the time for the community to think of something new and original to revolutionize the way we share files. The Pirate Bay did it job perfectly for over a decade and now seems like a perfect time for it do disappear from the Internet. In the meantime, Old Pirate Bay seems like a pretty decent alternative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting read by Peter Sunde: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.co.uk/news/archive/2014-12/11/peter-sunde&quot;&gt;I went to jail for my cause. What did you do?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Material Design in Linux</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///linux/2014/12/14/material-design-in-linux/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-14T03:02:24+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//linux/2014/12/14/material-design-in-linux</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;First of all, I do realize that I’m probably a few months late to talk about this topic. This topic is far from something new and something groundbreaking. Don’t believe me? Well, this video from Google now has well over 2 million views.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Q8TXgCzxEnw&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what exactly is material design? Well, it’s a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Design_language&quot;&gt;design language&lt;/a&gt; developed by Google. The whole point of this design language is that every graphical user interface should be as simple and colorful as possible. The point of that is, of course, to provide users with an interface which is pretty appealing to the eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google already implemented material design in the newest version of Android called Lollipop. You can easily see the whole point of material design by looking at this excellent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=cLYE3fgWI_4&quot;&gt;Android 5.0 Lollipop Review&lt;/a&gt; done by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theverge.com/&quot;&gt;The Verge&lt;/a&gt; guys. The plan for Google is to implement this design language to every single one of their services.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linux community embraced the whole material design idea pretty quickly. So, we already have this thing called &lt;a href=&quot;http://quantum-os.github.io/&quot;&gt;Quantum OS&lt;/a&gt; (previously known as Quartz OS). The point of this project is to create an operating system (which will probably be based on Arch Linux) that will follow Google’s own &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.google.com/design/spec/material-design/introduction.html&quot;&gt;material design guidelines&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember reading somewhere that it’s not fair to the KDE community to say that they’ve implemented the material design because some of the KDE 5 mockups were out far before Google released the whole material design idea to the public. Anyway, KDE Plasma 5 does seem to fit the concept, as you can see by looking at one of the huge number of YouTube reviews if you search for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/results?search_query=kde+plasma+5&quot;&gt;KDE Plasma 5&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And now I came to the whole point of writing this post. I found out about a material design solution that I can implement right now using my current setup. As you may know already, I’m a huge &lt;a href=&quot;http://elementaryos.org/&quot;&gt;elementary OS&lt;/a&gt; fan. elementary uses Pantheon as a DE, which is based on GNOME and uses GTK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, today, &lt;a href=&quot;http://snwh.org/&quot;&gt;Sam Hewitt&lt;/a&gt; published the first GTK theme (at least that I know about) that was created with the goal of implementing the rules of material design. The theme is called &lt;a href=&quot;http://snwh.org/paper/&quot;&gt;Paper&lt;/a&gt; and it’s in alpha stage at the moment. It looks wonderful and I’m pretty happy with how well the theme integrated with my elementary OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://snwh.org/paper/screenshot.png&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to use it, all you need to do is to extract the folder called Paper in the tarball into your ‘/usr/share/themes’ directory and that’s it. If you experience some problems with the theme, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/snwh/paper-gtk-theme/issues&quot;&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is the proper place to report bugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that Sam will continue to work successfully on such a great GTK theme and that we will see more of the material design GTK themes soon!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Through the Algorithm (2014) To a Free World</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/human%20hacking/2014/12/07/algorithm-to-a-free-world/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-07T04:41:07+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/human%20hacking/2014/12/07/algorithm-to-a-free-world</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I like watching movies about hacking. There are only two possible outcomes of me watching this kind of movies: they’re fantastic OR they’re terrible. If the movie is fantastic, I’m going to enjoy it of course. But, if the movie is terrible, I’m going to laugh my ass of how stupidly hacking is displayed in that movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, this movie goes into that other group. It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3293462/&quot;&gt;Algorithm&lt;/a&gt; (like you haven’t seen that coming from the title of the post). I’m going to start my story by talking about how I found out about this movie.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple of hours ago I was just browsing my Twitter feed like I usually do. But this time, there was a certain link to a blog post that got my attention. It’s a post by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brandxindustries.com/blog/?author=52efd1c5e4b0c02e5a3ad902&quot;&gt;Jonathan Schiefer&lt;/a&gt;, a writer and a director of this film. In a post titled &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.brandxindustries.com/blog/2014/12/4/the-free-future-starts-now&quot;&gt;The Free Future Starts Now&lt;/a&gt;, he talks about how piracy changed the way he looks at his movie. He didn’t earn much from the movie (not even enough to compensate the money he spent making the movie), but still, he did something marvelous. He shared his movie with the world for free for 24 hours. He knew that after those 24 hours are over, the pirating of the movie is going to be unstoppable, but that didn’t stop him from doing that. Now, his movie is all over the internet, and he feels damn proud about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never done a movie review before (hell, I don’t remember even reading any), especially not in English (I’m just saying this because I’m not a native English speaker as you probably notices by now), but I will give it a go. That’s the least I can do for Jonathan and his excellent piece of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the first movie I ever rated on IMDb and it got a perfect 10 from me. The movie is a perfect example that you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; make a movie about hacking without making something up. Everything I saw in this movie &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; possible, and that’s something that really impressed me. It’s something that made this movie stand up from the rest of the similar movies I saw. &lt;em&gt;Everything seems possible&lt;/em&gt;. Although I didn’t like the way hackers are represented in the movie (I think of a hacker more in an ideological way, as someone who thinks outside the box, not as someone who breaks computer systems), I completely understand why Jonathan decided to represent hackers in such way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This movie covers a story about a hacker (or if you’re like me, the term cracker might work better for you) who will try to break into anything he wants. He went out of line once and broke into some government database, which was a big mistake (of course). His friends were tortured by the government because of that and in the end he himself got tortured because a friend of his betrayed him. After they tortured him, the government &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; offer him a job, something that would probably happen if this was a real life situation (think of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hector_Xavier_Monsegur&quot;&gt;Sabu&lt;/a&gt; as a perfect example). I don’t want to spoil everything so I’m not going to say anything more about the story. I highly suggest you to pirate the movie if you’re interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I liked even more than the story was the way the technology was described in the movie. He talks about Linux, about Tor browser, the disadvantages of the open WiFi network, the disadvantages of proprietary programming languages, and the main ideology of every hacker: that the information should be free.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jonathan even went one step ahead as he adopted those words from the movie in the real life by sharing the movie with the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As he said in the blog post I linked, it all started with the software. Then came the books. Next stop was sharing the music. Now, we’re at a stage where sharing movies is something we encounter with on a regular basis. And the next stop is going to be sharing small physical objects (by using 3D printers).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to end the post by sharing the last couple of sentences from the post Jonathan published, because I really think that those sentences cover it all:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“_When everything is free there won’t be any poor. There won’t be any wealth inequalities. There won’t be people starving because anyone can just print food. People won’t go into debt for the rest of their life to go to college because we’ll have equal access to information and art. There will be no tricking the ignorant because people won’t be ignorant because information will be free. _&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I’m crazy enough to believe I can help change the world. And the world I want is when the future is free!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Gaming on Linux Is Still Not Very Noob-Friendly (Witcher 2: Installation From Hell)</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/linux/2014/12/04/witcher-2-installation-from-hell/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-04T20:56:24+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/linux/2014/12/04/witcher-2-installation-from-hell</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I learned that gaming on Linux is still not very noob friendly. For a long while now I was looking for a first game to buy in my life. I’ve decided for Wither 2: Assassins of Kings. The game costs somewhere near $20 on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gog.com/&quot;&gt;GOG&lt;/a&gt; and I got the 60% discount deal so the game cost me $7.99 total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The game itself is big, and I mean &lt;em&gt;really _big. I needed to download over 19 gigabytes, but what the heck, I bought it because I wanted to play it, so I went ahead and started the download. On the first try, download failed after 3,5 GB with no apparent reason. My internet connection did not break or anything like that. I felt discouraged but I wanted to give it another go, so I started to download the game, _again&lt;/em&gt;. This time, I downloaded more than 7 GB of data and the download crashed again for no apparent reason.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no official GOG’s Linux download manager for now, but after some searching around I did manage to find the unofficial one called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Sude-/lgogdownloader/&quot;&gt;lgogdownloader&lt;/a&gt; (thank you GitHub!). So I went ahead and installed it. It’s a fine command line tool and it’s not really hard to figure it out. After spending a half an hour connecting it with my GOG account (don’t blame the developer of this tool, the fault is all mine) the time has come for me to try to download the game for the third time now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time, download was successfully finished and I had the game on my hard drive. Wow, finally, looks like I’m going to be able to play it! So after I extracted the whole 19 gigs of compressed data to a folder I felt very excited. Now all I had to do is to start the game and I’ll be able to play it, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, of course not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know what is a launcher file, so I thought that all I needed to do is to give execution privileges to that file and the game should start, right? Well, no, the launcher didn’t start because of some broken dependency. Thanks to the Ubuntu’s huge repository, installing the dependency was not that big of a deal, just a standard &lt;em&gt;apt-get install&lt;/em&gt; command. After that I will finally start the game and that would be it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Aaaand finally, the launcher started without any errors in the terminal!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now all I needed to do is to click on Launch Ga… WHAT??? Broken dependency, again? Oh what the hell, &lt;em&gt;sudo apt-get install libsdl2-2.0&lt;/em&gt; should do the trick, right? All done, it’s time to &lt;em&gt;finally&lt;/em&gt; start the game, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;WHAT??? The same error &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;? But I &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; installed &lt;em&gt;libsdl2-__2.0&lt;/em&gt;! Back to Firefox and search for the issue. Oh, so I installed the 64-bit version of the package but I need the 32-bit version to start the game? Sure, no problem, repeating the last command with _:i386 _in the end should do the trick. Start the game again, aaand get a broken dependency error again!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So looks like I need one more package? OK, this time I won’t repeat the same error, I’ll install the 32-bit version right away. Now I have to admit that after going through such trouble, I do feel kind of frustrated and I just want to play the damn game. My inner hacker is exhausted so he took a nap and woke up 50-year-old grudged man inside of me from the couch. Let’s see if he can finish the installation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, GOG laughs at my face and gives me another broken dependency. This time it’s a package called &lt;em&gt;openal&lt;/em&gt;. Sure, no problem, &lt;em&gt;sudo apt-get install openal&lt;/em&gt;. What, not in the repository? Let’s try to Google that. So I did manage to find the renamed package. Looks like it’s called &lt;em&gt;libopenal0a&lt;/em&gt;, so let’s install it. &lt;em&gt;sudo apt-get install libopenal0a&lt;/em&gt;. Wait, no release candidate? Let’s Google some more. And while I’m searching for the solution, let’s look at GOG’s support, might want to contact them if something goes wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the officially supported distros are Ubuntu and Linux Mint. Oh, crap, I’m not using &lt;em&gt;them&lt;/em&gt;, I’m using &lt;a href=&quot;http://elementaryos.org/&quot;&gt;elementary OS&lt;/a&gt;! I don’t think that the support will be willing to help me out, but they do have &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; articles posted in their support section and elementary _is _built on top of Ubuntu 14.04, so I might check out those articles while I’m already at the support section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Question: &lt;em&gt;How do I start the game I unpacked from a tarball (*.tar.gz)?
_Solution: _Run ./start.sh&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, wait a second, I don’t have any shell scripts inside my Witcher folder, but I do have the launcher, which is practically the same, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Question: &lt;em&gt;Why do you list required libraries on the game’s product card?
_Solution: _… We’ll always make sure to include a list of any potentially missing libraries that make up a game’s minimum system requirements.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you GOG! So all I have to do is to find minimum system requirements and I’ll find the list of all packages I need to install and then I’ll be able to run the game! I remember I saw a file called &lt;em&gt;readme_EN.rtf&lt;/em&gt; inside of my Witcher folder. So I opened it up and navigated to system requirements section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What??? Linux is not even on this list??? Only requirements for Windows? What the hell? Back to Google-ing. Oh, marvelous! &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.webupd8.org/2014/05/the-witcher-2-assassins-of-kings-game.html&quot;&gt;Webupd8’s article&lt;/a&gt; about the game release for Linux does contain the system requirements section. Now let’s look for that list of packages I need. WAIT WHAT??? THE GAME ONLY SUPPORTS NVIDIA GPUs??? WHY IS THAT INFO NOT SHARED ON GOG’s SITE???&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, it is. Crap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OK, calm down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;cd ..
rm -r the_witcher_2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note to myself: Next time, buy the damn game on Steam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DISCLAIMER:&lt;/strong&gt; I love GOG, this text is not an attack on them in any way. This is just a satire text to show you my stupidity.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Korišćenje pravog identiteta nije pravi način da se spriječi govor mržnje na internetu</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///no%20hate%20speech%20online/2014/12/04/anonimnost-nije-rjesenje/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-04T15:40:25+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//no%20hate%20speech%20online/2014/12/04/anonimnost-nije-rjesenje</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Kao što sam već napisao &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/12/03/no-hate-speech-online/&quot;&gt;u prethodnom postu&lt;/a&gt; u &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/category/no-hate-speech-online/&quot;&gt;No Hate Speech Online&lt;/a&gt; kategoriji, učlanio sam se u radionice čiji je cilj umanjiti govor mržnje na internetu u našoj lokalnoj zajednici. Uspjeli u tome ili ne, glavni cilj radionica jeste da se tema pokrene i da se među nama mladima govor mržnje na internetu shvati kao jedan od problema digitalnog doba. Međutim, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kp7ww3KvccE&quot;&gt;u videu&lt;/a&gt; kojem sam postavio u prethodnom postu kao jedan od prijedloga se spominje korišćenje pravog identiteta prilikom izražavanja mišljenja na internetu (4:28). Pošto se tome protivim u potpunosti, odlučio sam da preko ovog posta izrazim svoje mišljenje i time potaknem diskusiju na našim sledjećim radionicama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uzeću sebe kao primjer i način na koji ja koristim, kako društvene mreže, tako i ovaj blog. Na nekim od društvenih mreža (Facebook, Google+, ovaj blog i “poslovni” Twitter profil koji koristim za ovaj blog) koristim svoj pravi identitet, dok se na nekim društvenim mrežama ne predstavljam svojim pravim identitetom (Reddit i “lični” Twitter profil).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iako podržavam pokret &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nohatespeechmovement.org/&quot;&gt;protiv govora mržnje na internetu&lt;/a&gt;, još više podržavam slobodu govora na internetu i smatram internet alatom preko kojeg se mogu desiti neke promjene i van virtualnog svijeta. Iako su brojna istraživanja dokazala da je anonimnost na internetu zapravo loša za suzbijanje govora mržnje na internetu*, ne smatram da je rješenje potpuno ukidanje anonimnosti na internetu, iako je to nešto čemu vodeće internet kompanije teže već dugo vremena, počevši od masivne upotrebe Facebook-a pa sve do manje-više bezuspješnog pokušaja uvođenja Google+ računa sa pravim identitetom za ostavljanje komentara na YouTube-u.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jedno je sigurno, anonimnost na internetu ima svojih prednosti i mana. Kao jedna od mana svakako jeste ta da će “average Joe” (prosječni korisnik interneta) vrlo vjerovatnije ostavljati manje govora mržnje koristeći svoj pravi identitet nego kada stoji iza anonimnog identiteta, međutim prisiljavanje korisnika servisa da za svoje izražavanje na servisu koriste svoj pravi identitet iza sebe donosi mnogo više mana.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9I7AGRUPIIE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Korišćenje svog pravog identiteta u bilo čemu što radimo na internetu umanjuje našu privatnost. Svako od nas ima nešto što želi da sakrije od nekoga. Samim time što iznosimo više problema pod svojim pravim identitetom ne odvlačimo ljude od toga da ljudi o nama šire govore mržnje, već produbljujemo moguće posljedice govora mržnje zato što naše postupke povezujemo direktno sa našim pravim identitetom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iz navedenih razloga smatram da forsiranje korišćenja pravog identiteta nije idealno rješenje. Isto tako ne smatram niti da je potpuna suprotnost toga (potpuna anonimnost na svim internet servisima) idealno rješenje. Smatram da je idealno rješenje dati korisnicima izbor da li žele da koriste svoj pravi identitet ili da ostanu anonimni. Samim time korisnici biraju kako žele da iznesu svoje mišljenje i svojom odlukom odlučuju i o tome koliko lično žele da prime govore mržnje.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Zaključak na osnovu sjećanja, ne mogu trenutno da pronađem neko istraživanje da pokrijem tu izjavu.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Pokret protiv govora mržnje na internetu</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///no%20hate%20speech%20online/2014/12/03/no-hate-speech-online/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-03T01:11:49+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//no%20hate%20speech%20online/2014/12/03/no-hate-speech-online</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/nohate.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/nohate.png&quot; alt=&quot;nohate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Govor mržnje je, govoreći van okvira zakona, svaki govor kojim se napada osoba ili određena grupa osoba na temelju njihovih atributa kao što su spol, etnička pripadnost, religija, rasa, invalidnost ili njihova seksualna orijentacija.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovo je prevedeni citat iz engleskog članka na Wikipediji za pojam govora mržnje (zašto ne volim domaće Wikipedije je već tema za drugi blog post). E sada kombinujte govor mržnje sa slobodom govora na internetu i dobija se nešto potpuno uznemirujuće.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Da budemo iskreni, sa govorom mržnje na internetu se susrećemo svakodnevno, dok na skoro pa svakodnevnoj bazi i sami učestvujemo u njima, svjesno ili ne. U digitalnom dobu u kojem tek počinjemo da živimo na našim prostorima govor mržnje postaje jedan od glavnih problema sa kojima se susrećemo. Trajno rješenje ovog problema koje bi se moglo odmah sprovesti jednostavno ne postoji i potrebno je da svako na svoj način doprinese “ljepšem internetu”. Velika je vjerovatnoća da ste čuli onu čuvenu izjavu “internet ne pripada nikome, ali u isto vrijeme internet pripada svima nama”. E pa o tome se i radi, internet je baš onakav kakvim ga mi kreiramo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smatram da je najbolji način da se dođe do rješenja tog problema tako da se zapravo priča o njemu kao o problemu današnjice. Smatrajući da je to jedan od vrlo bitnih problema sa kojima se susrećemo, odlučio sam se priključiti radionicama u mom gradu koje se održavaju pod nazivom &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/pages/No-Hate-Online-No-Hate-Offline/579839252093782&quot;&gt;No Hate Online - No Hate Offline&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neću zauzimati ogroman dio ovog posta da bih pričao o tome kako su radionice nastale i ko sve stoji iza njih (mada ne isključujem mogućnost da tome posvetim poseban post na blogu) jer smatram da je sama njihova poenta sasvim jasna: okupiti mlade ljude i kroz razgovor sa njima uticati na njih i na ostale mlade ljude oko njih i kroz razgovor se postepeno boriti protiv govora mržnje na internetu. Iako smo svjesni da mi kao grupa ne možemo puno toga da uradimo, smatramo se pojedinicima koji su spremni da načnu tu “pandorinu kutiju”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovaj post je više introdukcija na neku novu temu kojoj planiram da posvetim prostor na svom blogu nego post koji će konkretno da se bavi problemom. Već imam u glavi pripremljenu temu za sledjećih nekoliko postova, tako da ukoliko vas zanima kako se ja kao pojedinac i mi kao grupa odnosimo prema problemu, obratite pažnju na novu kategoriju postova na blogu pod nazivom &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/category/no-hate-speech-online/&quot;&gt;No Hate Speech Online&lt;/a&gt;, gdje će se nalaziti svi moji postovi vezani za ovu temu na jednom mjestu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kp7ww3KvccE&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>CodeCombat – The Most Fun Way To Learn New Programming Language</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///linux/projects/2014/12/02/codecombat/"/>
   <updated>2014-12-02T01:38:30+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//linux/projects/2014/12/02/codecombat</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/about_comic.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/about_comic.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;about_comic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you ever programmed in your life, you’ve probably realized that the process of learning a new programming language can become quite a boring thing to do. You already know how to program in X programming language, but you need to learn the syntax of Y language for yourself / for some new project / for some job you want to get? Well, believe it or not, there _is _a fun way to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was never a huge fan of video games, but I did like to play a game or two once every few days. I haven’t played a single game for months now. I consider playing games as a huge procrastination. One of the main reasons I switched to Linux (almost completely now) is because I wanted to be more productive, and one of the ways to be more productive is to limit your access to the things that make you procrastinate*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, there’s a certain game that got my attention. It’s called &lt;a href=&quot;http://codecombat.com/&quot;&gt;CodeCombat&lt;/a&gt; and the point of playing this game is to teach you the syntax of a programming language in a very fun way. It’s an open source project (and if you’ve been reading my blog you know how much am I obsessed by everything related to open source) and the game is not limited to one specific programming language. You can select which programming language you want to use. My choice for a new programming language was JavaScript. This is a pretty well done browser game, so you can start playing the game no matter what platform you’re using currently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now I’m not in any way suggesting that this is the best way to learn some programming language, but it pretty much is the most fun way of doing that. So, if you like playing computer games, but you think that you’re waisting your time by playing them instead of learning something, this game is pretty much the best of both worlds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/trailer_1.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/12/trailer_1.png&quot; alt=&quot;trailer_1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;DISCLAIMER: I’m not saying that gaming on Linux is not possible. I’m a huge fan of the way how Linux gaming is advancing in the last year or two. I’m just having a huge self control over it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 3: See Locked Profile Picture in Full Size</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///cyber%20security/projects/2014/11/20/facebook-hack-no3/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-20T13:38:08+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//cyber%20security/projects/2014/11/20/facebook-hack-no3</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I found out about one more basic Facebook hack. Let’s say that you have a friend who locked his profile picture so that nobody could open it, but you’re interested to see &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; that picture looks in full size. Can you do that? Well, thanks to Facebook’s constant consern about user privacy, of course you can.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what you need to do? You just need to use this URL:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://graph.facebook.com/USERNAME/picture?width=800&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, you need to replace the string USERNAME with the actual username of the user. You can get that by just opening up that profile and checking the URL in your browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, this works even if you don’t have that person in your friends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the third time, thank you Facebook!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the rest of the Facebook “hacks” here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/13/facebook-hack-no1/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” - Hack no. 1: Check who’s your biggest “stalker” without leaving Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/13/facebook-hack-no2/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” - Hack no. 2: Find out who’s calling you on your phone by using Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/12/15/facebook-hack-no4/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 4: DDoS a Website By Using Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>I'm Joining Mozillians!</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/mozilla%20firefox/projects/2014/11/14/im-joining-mozillians/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-14T18:04:56+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/mozilla%20firefox/projects/2014/11/14/im-joining-mozillians</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, this is my second (or maybe even third?) time trying to join the Mozilla community. The previous attempts did not go as I thought they will, so I’m ready to start again. In my previous attempt I tried to contact my local Mozilla community, but they seem to be pretty inactive these days so that attempt didn’t go too well. Anyway, it’s time to try again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do I want to try again exactly?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it’s been a couple of years since I started using Mozilla’s service in every opportunity I get. I’m using Firefox and Thunderbird all of the time, I started chatting on IRC regularly (you can find me on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.freenode.org/&quot;&gt;Freenode&lt;/a&gt; almost all of the time), I do have some kind of coding skills and thanks to &lt;a href=&quot;http://elementaryos.org/&quot;&gt;elementary OS&lt;/a&gt;, I started to feel pretty confident in testing out beta software. Other than that, I do have a lot of translation experience, translating projects like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/r3bl/&quot;&gt;reddit&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://torproject.org/&quot;&gt;The Tor Project&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://elementaryos.org/&quot;&gt;elementary OS&lt;/a&gt; (and all of the software it contains by default) and the list goes on and on. I also happened to have a lot of free time lately, so the only question is why shouldn’t I help a project that’s doing so much to help us who use free software regularly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;So, what I will be doing then?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m going to test out Mozilla’s services as much as I can. I’m going to help my local team to translate all of the products to Bosnian language, and, if I start to feel confident enough, I’m going to start writing some code for Mozilla in my spare time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Come and join us!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Come and join us at &lt;a href=&quot;https://mozillians.org/en-US/&quot;&gt;mozillians.org&lt;/a&gt;! You can find my freshly created profile there by visiting &lt;a href=&quot;https://mozillians.org/en-US/u/aleksandar.todorovic/&quot;&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the start, it’s time for me to stop writing this blog post and check out my mail, join the Mozilla’s IRC and so on and so on. I hope that this attempt is going to be much much better than my previous one and that I’m going to start contributing to Mozilla on a regular basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/mozilla.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/mozilla.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 2: Find out who's calling you on your phone by using Facebook</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///cyber%20security/projects/2014/11/13/facebook-hack-no2/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-13T15:58:56+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//cyber%20security/projects/2014/11/13/facebook-hack-no2</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I’ve already said &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/13/facebook-hack-no1/&quot;&gt;in my previous post&lt;/a&gt;, In this blog post series I’m going to post about some useful Facebook “hacks” that you can do without ever leaving Facebook at all. I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be using any external software, website or something similar while posting about this topic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have some mobile numbers but you don’t know who’s behind them? Well, Facebook automatically allows you to search users by their mobile number, so all you have to do is to enter that phone number in Facebook’s search. There is absolutely no option for you to disable that what so ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a lot easier to find someone if you have them as your friends, you’ll get a lot more exact information that way, because the default privacy setting for this is limited to friends only. You can also do this with an email address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A fun project&lt;/strong&gt;: Create an Android/iPhone/Windows Phone/FirefoxOS application. When someone unknown number calls you, the application opens up Facebook and enters that mobile number in Facebook’s search and displays the top result to you, so you know who’s calling you even if you don’t have them inside your address book.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to make this kind of application, please do let me know. I’m willing to use it and I’m willing to share it on my blog. I’m just lazy as fuck, so I won’t be creating that application any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might want to check out other posts in this series:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/13/facebook-hack-no1/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 1: Check who’s your biggest “stalker” without leaving Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/20/facebook-hack-no3/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 3: See Locked Profile Picture in Full Size&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/12/15/facebook-hack-no4/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 4: DDoS a Website By Using Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Some Basic Facebook "Hacks" - Hack no. 1: Check who's your biggest "stalker" without leaving Facebook</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///cyber%20security/projects/2014/11/13/facebook-hack-no1/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-13T15:41:19+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//cyber%20security/projects/2014/11/13/facebook-hack-no1</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this blog post series I’m going to post about some useful Facebook “hacks” that you can do without ever leaving Facebook at all. I will &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; be using any external software, website or something similar while posting about this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to see who checks your profile the most, reads your stories and stuff like that? Well, Facebook automatically adds some points to an account for stuff like that and you can check out who’s currently your biggest “stalker” by following the description described here. I recommend you to use Firefox, it’s a lot easier to do this in Firefox than it is in Chrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open up your Facebook’s homepage.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ctrl + U.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ctrl + F. Type InitialChatFriendsList in the find bar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;After that string you’ll see a long number inside “” that ends with -2. Copy that number &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; -2 in the end.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Go to https://www.facebook.com/&lt;em&gt;pastethatnumberhere&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Voila!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re using Chrome, Ctrl + F in the page inspector does not work as you’d expected it to work so my suggestion is to copy the entire page source to your favorite text editor and search from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might want to check out other posts in this series:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/13/facebook-hack-no2/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 2: Find out who’s calling you on your phone by using Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/20/facebook-hack-no3/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 3: See Locked Profile Picture in Full Size&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/12/15/facebook-hack-no4/&quot;&gt;Some Basic Facebook “Hacks” – Hack no. 4: DDoS a Website By Using Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Changing the design of my blog, desktop and twitter account</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/linux/projects/2014/11/12/changing-the-design/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-12T23:18:36+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/linux/projects/2014/11/12/changing-the-design</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I feel pretty cyberpunk-ish lately so I’ve decided to change the whole look of three most important things to me: my blog, my Twitter account and my desktop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m really feeling this concept art by a great artist called &lt;a href=&quot;http://andreewallin.com/&quot;&gt;Andree Wallin&lt;/a&gt;. The art I like the most is called &lt;a href=&quot;http://andreewallin.deviantart.com/art/Headphones-346542540&quot;&gt;Headphones&lt;/a&gt; so I’ve decided to use it as my main inspiration for the design. So this is how my desktop looks like right now:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/screenshot-from-2014-11-12-022234.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/screenshot-from-2014-11-12-022234.png?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot from 2014-11-12 02:22:34&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/screenshot-from-2014-11-12-022237.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/11/screenshot-from-2014-11-12-022237.png?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot from 2014-11-12 02:22:37&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what I did is I changed the background and then started to edit my Gtk theme and &lt;a href=&quot;http://speedracker.deviantart.com/art/Purple-Rain-Conky-485091413&quot;&gt;Purple Rain&lt;/a&gt; Conky configuration file. I did loose a couple of hours doing that, but I’m pretty satisfied with it right now and I’m getting a lot of positive feedback all over Google+ and Reddit for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next thing I freshened up the design of my blog. So I’ve changed the theme and customized it a little. Hope this design works better for you. If not, contact me of course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Twitter is also re-designed, which means I basically only changed my avatar, header photo and the colour scheme, so I don’t have a lot to talk about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh, and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/11/11/elementary-os-bosnian-language/&quot;&gt;translation of elementary OS&lt;/a&gt; is going great! Although, I have to admit that I’m not a huge fan of Launchpad as a tool for the translation of such a big project.&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What I've been doing lately? Translating elementary OS!</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/linux/projects/2014/11/11/elementary-os-bosnian-language/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-11T15:07:18+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/linux/projects/2014/11/11/elementary-os-bosnian-language</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, apart from writing my first semi-professional paper (which I wrote about – although in Bosnian - &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/10/28/da-li-su-dobri-muzicki-producenti-ujedno-i-dobri-psiholozi-eksperiment/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) and organizing a contest on my blog where you could win a couple of Office 365 licenses for free, I started to fall in love into programming again. It’s been a couple of months since I programmed &lt;em&gt;anything&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last project I’ve been working on is working, but it has a hell of a lot of bugs. It’s called Sensitive Data Grabber and I’ve already written about it on my blog &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/08/03/sensitive-data-grabber-project/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. So, why ain’t I finishing it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, the thing is that I’ve created that project using Visual Basic inside Visual Studio. You probably know that this kind of environment is Windows-specific. I’ve been spending most of my time lately using Linux as my primary operating system. I’ve found my perfect distribution and it’s called elementary OS (I already covered the reasons why &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/10/16/elementary-os-savrsena-distribucija-za-mene/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; - again, in Bosnian language).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, because I don’t have enough knowledge in any programming language that can be run in my perfect distribution, I’m still adjusting. While I’m doing that, I’ve decided that I want to do &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; for the elementary community &lt;em&gt;before&lt;/em&gt; I’m good enough to program some apps. Because of that, I’ve decided to start translating elementary OS to Bosnian language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not just getting started, I’ve already finished translating a lot of elementary-related projects. Now I only have seven (out of 37) projects left. That’s a little more than 2.5k strings to translate. It does seem like a lot, but I’m pretty confident that I will be able to finish that by the end of the year. Most of the operating system is already translated. By the time I finish it, I’ll probably be able to program some useful apps and then I’ll start to publish them using my own ppa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I feel very optimistic right now. As the narrator says in the end of this great video:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I don’t know why, but.. I feel very excited about the future. Anything is possible now.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mp-IZEFqrG0&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The translation of elementary OS is almost over! Only a couple of programs until you can use elementary OS without any problems if you come from Bosnia &amp;amp; Herzegovina!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>[Office 365 Giveaway] Winners announced!</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/projects/2014/11/06/office-giveaway-winners/"/>
   <updated>2014-11-06T12:03:42+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/projects/2014/11/06/office-giveaway-winners</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A few days back I published &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/10/30/get-free-office365-license/&quot;&gt;this article &lt;/a&gt;where I created a small giveaway, two Office 365 licenses for two of the best short stories I get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, it’s time for me to declare winners. Both of the winners are from reddit’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/pcmasterrace&quot;&gt;PC Master Race subreddit&lt;/a&gt; and both of them had written some great short stories about Gaben’s road to success! The winners are: [/u/Stannis&lt;em&gt;](https://www.reddit.com/user/Stannis&lt;/em&gt;) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/user/hobbit9797&quot;&gt;/u/hobbit9797&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to everyone for their participation! This post will be updated once I get in contact with winners with a screenshot as a proof that this contest was not a scam in any way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end of the post, I’m sharing the stories in their original form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A story from /u/Stannis_:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many years ago, before the days of the Steam, there lived a peasant, his daily routine was to come home from school, play CoD and have intercourse with mothers around the world, then one day while watching some video about the Xbox one announcement he spotted something on the side bar, slowly his cursor moved to the right like a lion hunting its prey, it hovered over the title, “how to build a gaming PC”, he seldom viewed anything about PC’s, with wonders flowing through his mind he pressed on the LMB.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He was amazed, the idea of being able to play Skyrim in 1920x1080 at 60fps, it seemed like something of a myth, the idea of playing a game in such a glorious fashion, his jaw dropped and almost shattered his keyboard, he saw the links appear across the screen, the purchase took place a week later, each part coming in one by one, he pieced the machine together like the assembly of a car, each part falling into place, the case was shut, the power button pushed, the operating system installed and the journey of a better gaming experience had begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Praise GabeN, and thanks for the giveaway.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A story from /u/hobbit9797:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the beach, where one wave was sucking a single shingle, I met a man. He told me about his life. He once had an idea. He wanted to create a system on which mankind could play for eternity and he had a dream…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I saw a landscape beautiful and untouched. There was a beach with single waves hitting the shingles on the shore and three birds are flying in a white sky. I heard the sound of a trombone and masses of men came down from the sky and rose from the ground. They were clothed in robes green and blue and black. In a time that felt likey minutes they constructed entire cities and factory halls and office buildings.
The beach perished and instead of birds there were black blocks of plastic and metal in a dark grey sky. When the mey finished their construction, they began to fight over which block was the best. Which block had the most ‘features’. Which block looked best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The men soon disappeared one after another but the black blocks stood firm with flashing red lights coming out from them. Then I heard a second trombone and a deep and strong voice said: ‘Let it be new!’. The blocks crumbled and became shingles again. The sky cleared up and was white first and then blue. Birds came flying from the ocean and filled the sky with their sound. It was good.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scared by his dream he decided to live alone on the beach. He dreamt about one day when his idea of a perfect gaming system finally comes alive. But whenever he tried to build with electronics, the static discharge destroyed his works. And he kept being a mad man dreaming about black cases, television and game discs…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somewhere else another man had the same dream. But unlike the first man he was gifted. He created the one system to rule the all. A system that is as complex as easy to work with. A system that could shatter the black dream blocks by its pure existenc. This system was his personal computer…&lt;/p&gt;

</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Get Office 365 License For Free! [A Little Contest]</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/human%20hacking/linux/projects/2014/10/30/get-free-office365-license/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-30T18:40:30+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/human%20hacking/linux/projects/2014/10/30/get-free-office365-license</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, even though I’m a regular Linux user, I use Microsoft’s software whenever I need them. I’ve bought an Office 365 Home Plus license in July of this year. So, what did I get with it? I got five Home subscriptions, each one with a licensed Office suite, 1 TB of OneDrive space and some premium Skype minutes (I can’t remember how many exactly). The license expires in July, but I will renew it as soon as it expires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After using this license for a couple of months now, I still have two licenses laying around without an owner and I’ve decided to share it with you guys for free! The only requirement for this contest is that you have Windows 7 or newer installed on your PC because the older versions are not supported with this version of Office suite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now considering that probably more than two people are interested in getting it, I’ve decided to create a little contest. All you have to do is to write some short story and send it to me. I don’t have any specific theme that I want you to write about, you can write about anything you want to, but I will prefer the topics that I’m interested in than those that I am not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those topics include anything related to open source, hacking, Linux, PC Master Race, NSA spying, artificial intelligence, social engineering or human psychology. You can write your story in any language I know: English, Bosnian, Serbian or Croatian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to know something about you. I want to hear your story and learn something from your experience and I’m ready to give you $80 worth software just to hear your story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can send your stories to my email address (&lt;a href=&quot;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;:&amp;#097;&amp;#108;&amp;#101;&amp;#107;&amp;#115;&amp;#097;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#046;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#111;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#099;&amp;#064;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#046;&amp;#114;&amp;#117;&quot;&gt;&amp;#097;&amp;#108;&amp;#101;&amp;#107;&amp;#115;&amp;#097;&amp;#110;&amp;#100;&amp;#097;&amp;#114;&amp;#046;&amp;#116;&amp;#111;&amp;#100;&amp;#111;&amp;#114;&amp;#111;&amp;#118;&amp;#105;&amp;#099;&amp;#064;&amp;#109;&amp;#097;&amp;#105;&amp;#108;&amp;#046;&amp;#114;&amp;#117;&lt;/a&gt;), just put [Office Contest] in the beginning of the email subject. I will select two stories that I like the most and share the license with them. I will probably publish the winning stories on my blog with the explanation on why I chose them. The contest ends on November the 5th. The winners will be announced on November the 6th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s a picture as a proof that I have two licenses available right now (excuse my poor GIMP knowledge):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/screenshot-from-2014-10-30-181831.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.files.wordpress.com/2014/10/screenshot-from-2014-10-30-181831.png?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;Screenshot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Da li su dobri muzički producenti ujedno i dobri psiholozi? [eksperiment]</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/human%20hacking/projects/2014/10/28/da-li-su-dobri-muzicki-producenti-ujedno-i-dobri-psiholozi-eksperiment/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-28T15:36:42+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/human%20hacking/projects/2014/10/28/da-li-su-dobri-muzicki-producenti-ujedno-i-dobri-psiholozi-eksperiment</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NAPOMENA: Ovaj članak nije ograničen na neki muzički žanr, preporučujem svim čitaocima da ga pročitaju bez obzira šta da slušate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U &lt;a href=&quot;http://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/10/26/libre-28-slobodni-softver-i-internet-stvari-1-deo/&quot;&gt;prethodno objavljenom postu&lt;/a&gt; sam već najavio svoje najnoviji rad na temu o tome da li muzika može da utiče na ponašanje određene osobe. Prije nekih 10 dana sam počeo da se bavim time i još uvijek sam fazi pisanja draftova i traženja kvalitetne literature da bih uradio rad na nivou.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Međutim, tokom mog procesa traženja materijala, naišao sam na &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/MuzIndustrija/status/526644272452231168&quot;&gt;jedan zanimljiv tvit&lt;/a&gt; koji tvrdi da je dobar muzički producent ujedno i dobar psiholog. Nisam ga razumio, pa sam odlučio da pročitam članak na koji se taj tvit odnosi. To me je dovelo do &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.muzickaindustrija.com/podela-rada-u-muzickoj-industriji-producenti/&quot;&gt;ovog članka&lt;/a&gt; u kojem se objašnjava šta je tačno muzički producent. U članku se samo nekoliko puta spominje ta izjava bez detaljnog objašnjenja kako tačno muzički producenti utiču na psihu kod ljudi, temu koju objašnjavam u svom radu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Da bih samo dodirnuo površinu toga, odlučio sam da malo prostudiram temu u obliku ovog posta, čisto da zaintrigiram vašu maštu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dakle, dobar muzički producent je ujedno i dobar psiholog. To je izjava iza koje stojim. Potrudiću se da ukratko objasnim i zašto.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Svi smo tokom svog života čuli makar jednu pjesmu u kojoj je tekstopisac pogodio neku našu bolnu tačku i natjerao nas da se osjećamo na određeni način na koji smo se osjećali. Međutim, mnogo manje pažnje se posvećuje muzičkim producentima, ljudima koji muziku ukomponuju sa tekstom i preko nje izraze svoje emocije. Zašto je to tako, trenutno ne mogu da sa sigurnošću tvrdim. Jedini razlog koji mi pada na pamet jeste taj što se samoj muzici moramo u potpunosti prepustiti da bi ona izazvala u nama ono nešto, dok to nije jednak slučaj i sa tekstovima u pjesmama.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zato želim da uradim jedan eksperiment. Izazivam vas da na nekom malo kvalitetnijem ozvučenju (bile to slušalice, malo kvalitetniji zvučnici ili nešto treće) poslušate sledjeće pjesme. Dakle jedino što ne dolazi u obzir jeste slušanje preko telefona, zvučnika od laptopa ili slušalica od jedan euro. Ja ću vam tačno opisati kako će vas pjesma natjerati da se osjećate, a vi me slobodno kontaktirajte i recite mi da li sam pogriješio ili ne. Poslušajte pjesmu sa zatvorenim očima, nakon što se pjesma završi, pročitajte tekst u kojem sam opisao tačno kako ćete se osjećati dok slušate pjesmu i napravite usporedbu. Garantujem da će se mišljenja poklopiti u minimalno tri od pet slučajeva.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Prva pjesma: Netsky - Lost In This World&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=svW2KL-9KQI&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sam žanr ove pjesme vam se možda nije svidio, ali ste se osjećali uznemireno dok ste je slušali. Kroz misli vam je prošla osoba koju ste nekad imali, ali je izgubili. Mislili ste o njoj, osjećali ste se nervozno i u vama je počela da se nakuplja određena doza bijesa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Druga pjesma: The xx - Intro&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=3gxNW2Ulpwk&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Za razliku od prvog eksperimenta, ova pjesma nije dotaknula vaše emocije u negativnom smislu. Zapravo nije ih dotakla ni u dobrom smislu. Sve što ste osjećali jeste osjećaj relaksacije, i svi problemi su nestali na tih nekoliko minuta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Treća pjesma: Blackmill feat. Veela - Life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ciidn3nEoiE&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zbog ove pjesme ste se osjećali srećno. Osjećali ste kako se nalazite na nekoj plaži, toplo sunce vas je grijalo, a vi ste se osjećali bespokojno. U glavi ste imali osjećaj kao da su svi problemi postepeno nestali, a do kraja pjesme ste imali osjećaj kao da ste upravo proživjeli jedan od najljepših trenutak vašeg života.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Četvrta pjesma: Noisia - Tommy’s Theme&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jjbiMXfe2NU&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Osjećali ste se prljavo. Zamislilili ste se u nekoj post-apokaliptičnoj situaciji u kojoj je čitav svijet uništen ljudskom glupošću. Sav bijes je u vama proradio u tom trenutku.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Peta (i posljednja) pjesma: Porter Robinson - Unison&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Y_J3WWYp8Gc&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovo je vrlo posebna pjesma na listi jer ne budi jedno osjećanje u slušaocima, nego više njih. U samom početku niste znali šta da očekujete i kako da se osjećate. Kada se taj dio pjesme završio i kada je krenuo drugi, osjećali ste se opušteno, svaka nota vam je odgovarala, čak i ona jedna jedina za koju ste u tom jednom trenutku pomislili da je pogrešno odsvirana. Međutim, na vaše iznenađenje, pjesma je krenula da vas diže, da se osjećate živo. I tu je završio drugi dio pjesme. U trećem dijelu pjesme ste se osjećali onako kako zamišljate da ćete da osjećate kada bi nekada probali neku drogu. Sav ovaj proces se još jednom ponovio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukoliko vas je članak zaintrigirao, pozivam vas da mi se javite i da podijelite sa mnom rezultate ovog eksperimenta. Javiti mi se možete na nekoliko načina, &lt;a href=&quot;aleksandar.todorovic@mail.ru&quot;&gt;putem mail-a&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/coa.brate.coa.brate&quot;&gt;koristeći Facebok&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/r3bl_&quot;&gt;Tviter&lt;/a&gt; ili komentirajući direktno ispod članka koristeći vaš Wordpress nalog.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>LiBRE! 28 - Slobodni softver i internet stvari (1. deo)</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/human%20hacking/projects/2014/10/26/libre-28-slobodni-softver-i-internet-stvari-1-deo/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-26T03:30:59+01:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/human%20hacking/projects/2014/10/26/libre-28-slobodni-softver-i-internet-stvari-1-deo</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Izašao je novi, &lt;a href=&quot;https://libre.lugons.org/index.php/broj-28/&quot;&gt;28. po redu broj LiBRE! časopisa&lt;/a&gt;. U ovom broju možete pročitati prvi dio teme &lt;em&gt;Slobodni softver i internet stvari&lt;/em&gt; koju obrađujem u ime LiBRE! tima.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U prvom dijelu sam se zapitao možemo li računati na softverske gigante u uvođenje slobodnog softvera u internet stvari. Pored toga sam napravio uvod u to kako tačno rade pametni uređaji te tako napravio uvod za drugi dio članka u kojem ću obrađivati Spark projekat koji sam izdvojio kao najzanimljiviji projekat vezan za internet stvari koji se fokusira u potpunosti na slobodne tehnologije u svom biznis modelu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ukoliko ne želite da skidate čitav broj da biste pročitali tekst, tekst možete da preuzmete i iz za to &lt;a href=&quot;http://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/projects-and-papers/&quot;&gt;posvećenog dijela&lt;/a&gt; moje web stranice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pored nastavljanja bavljenja ovom temom, u izradi je i moja prva ozbiljnija samostalna publikacija u kojoj se bavim u potpunosti drugačijom temom, uticajem muzike na ponašanje osobe. Ovo je prva tema koju obrađujem u svom cilju da savladam razumijevanje ljudskog ponašanja i načine preko kojih se ljudsko ponašanje može modifikovati u ličnu korist (&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_engineering_(security)&quot;&gt;pojam socijalni inžinjering&lt;/a&gt;). Kada rad bude završen, vratiću se regularnom blogingu.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>What exactly is a hacker?</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/human%20hacking/2014/10/18/what-exactly-is-a-hacker/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-18T12:28:54+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/human%20hacking/2014/10/18/what-exactly-is-a-hacker</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quote:&lt;/strong&gt;
_ Not to be confused, hacker is a person who wants to share his knowledge about computers with others. Hacker is every person who thinks in an unconventional way. An idea that a hacker is someone who does something malicious is an idea created in Hollywood._&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a quote from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=yD_MRddq0qg&quot;&gt;a report&lt;/a&gt; about a hacking convention called BalCCon 2k14 that took place for the second year in a row in Novi Sad, the second biggest city in Serbia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that this quote describes perfectly what a hacker is. I feel kinda tired of all those “you call yourself a hacker, you’re going to end up in jail” conversations and Google+ posts in hacker communities where idiots ask stuff like: “teach me how to hack fb plz”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do realize that 95% of people don’t understand us who call ourselves hackers and I do realize that they will probably never learn, but I feel so tired of this that I had to share this quote with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re not sure what a hacker is, I suggest you to start learning by reading this &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hacker_%28term%29&quot;&gt;Wikipedia article about a term hacker&lt;/a&gt;. You will start to realize that the hacker is a much more broader term than the one you have in mind, although I don’t think that this article explains it a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end of this post, I want to share another quote with you. This quote is from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schneier.com/&quot;&gt;Bruce Schneier&lt;/a&gt;’s book called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schneier.com/book-sandl.html&quot;&gt;Secrets and Lies (2000)&lt;/a&gt; and I think that this definition covers it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quote&lt;/strong&gt;
_ A hacker is someone who thinks outside the box. It’s someone who discards conventional wisdom, and does something else instead. It’s someone who looks at the edge and wonders what’s beyond. It’s someone who sees a set of rules and wonders what happens if you don’t follow them. A hacker is someone who experiments with the limitations of systems for intellectual curiosity._&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EDIT:
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.berkeley.edu/~bh/hacker.html&quot;&gt;Here are&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://compnetworking.about.com/od/networksecurityprivacy/f/what-is-hacking.htm&quot;&gt;some other articles&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.zdnet.com/blog/security/what-is-a-hacker/9468&quot;&gt;written about&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://searchsecurity.techtarget.com/definition/hacker&quot;&gt;what a term&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.schneier.com/blog/archives/2006/09/what_is_a_hacke.html&quot;&gt;hacker is&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>elementary OS - Savršena distribucija za mene</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/linux/2014/10/16/elementary-os-savrsena-distribucija-za-mene/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-16T22:16:17+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/linux/2014/10/16/elementary-os-savrsena-distribucija-za-mene</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sada sam tek shvatio da iako mi je blog pun postova o Linuksu, trenutno nemam niti jedan post posvećen u potpunosti distribuciji koja je zadovoljila sve kriterijume da bude savršeni operativni sistem za moje potrebe: elementary OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Već sam pisao ponešto o svojem putu koji me je doveo sve do elementary-a kada sam se pridružio &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?q=%23budiUbuntu&amp;amp;src=typd&quot;&gt;#budiUbuntu&lt;/a&gt; akciji blogeraša sa naših prostora &lt;a href=&quot;http://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/08/18/moj-put-od-fedore-preko-archa-do-ubuntu-derivata-budiubuntu/&quot;&gt;u ovom postu&lt;/a&gt;, tako da se neću puno zadržavati tu nego ću vam ispričati zašto je baš elementary OS savršena distribucija za mene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ako ste ikada čuli za &lt;a href=&quot;http://elementaryos.org/&quot;&gt;elementary OS&lt;/a&gt;, već znate da je prelijep. Nastao je kao fork Ubuntu-a sa željom da ga učine ljepšim. Prva verzija se zvala Jupiter i nemam ama baš nikakvih iskustva sa tom verzijom. Nakon toga slijedi Luna, i dalje aktuelna verzija elementary-a bazirana na Ubuntu 12.04 verziji i tu počinje moje putovanje, koje se sada nastavlja sa beta verzijama sledjećeg u nizu odličnih proizvoda elementary porodice: Freya.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pa šta ga izdvaja iz većine toliko da ga smatram savršenim operativnim sistemom? Prije svega, naravno, moram da izdvojim njegovu ljepotu. Dosta je minimalističan sistem, nakon svakog mog klika operativni sistem se odaziva istovremeno, nešto na šta nisam baš navikao koristeći KDE distribucije i Prozore u prošlosti. Tu je i odličan Ubuntu repozitorij programa, tako da se uopšte ne brinem za to da postoji neki program pisan za Linuks platformu koji ja ne mogu da pokrenem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;elementary koristi vlastiti DE pod nazivom Pantheon, DE koji radi savršeno i dolazi pred-instaliran sa svim programima koji će vam ikada biti potrebni: za slušanje muzike, gledanje videa i fotografija, čitanje dokumenata, pretraživanje interneta, čitanje mailova i slično. Svaki od programa je jednostavno prelijep i većinu nisam nikada ni promjenio, međutim neki od tih programa jednostavno ne pružaju dovoljno mogućnosti za mene, tako da konstantno preferiram Firefox umjesto Midorija, Thunderbird mi zamjenjuje Geary, a što se filmova tiče jednostavno nikada ni na jednoj platformi nisam uspio da se odviknem od korišćenja VLC plejera, bez obzira na to koliko je Audience savršen program i radi bez ikakvih poteškoća.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sistem jeste uveliko zatvoren i na sve strane se može čitati o tome kako njegovi developeri u dizajnu u mnogo čemu kopiraju Mac, međutim ne smatram ga kopijom Mac operativnog sistema iako postoje neke sličnosti koje ne mogu da se ne primjete.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jednostavno obožavam to što je sistem minimalistički i funkcionalan. Ukoliko se pronađe neka stvar koja mi ne odgovara (tipa nedostatak minimise opcije u programima), poprilično je lako pronaći rješenje za tako nešto. Ukoliko se javi neki problem koji je potrebno riješiti, to što je sistem baziran na Ubuntu-u je veliki plus i većina rješenja se može naći tako što se u internet tražilici unese opis problema i na kraju doda riječ elementary ili Ubuntu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Postoji neka draž u praćenju razvoja nekog operativnog sistema. To sam po prvi put osjetio kada sam instalirao Beta 1 verziju nove verzije operativnog sistema pod nazivom Freya. Iako mi se nakon same instalacije operativnog sistema promjene nisu činile toliko drastične da je potrebna nova verzija operativnog sistema za tako nešto, ekipa koja stoji iza elementary OS-a radi svakodnevno da donesu neke nove funkcije, neke nove izmjene u dizajnu i riješe neke nove bagove koje su mučile ovaj operativni sistem. Danas, nekoliko dana od Freya Beta 2 verzije, novi elementary se polako oblikuje u nešto fantastično. U nešto nevjerovatno. Neopisiv je osjećaj ponosa koji imam zbog toga što sam pratio to sve i učestvovao u njegovoj izradi prijavljivanjem ponekog baga i učestvovanjem u diskusiji u odličnoj &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/communities/104613975513761463450&quot;&gt;službenoj Google+ zajednici&lt;/a&gt; (koja je i jedini razlog zašto koristim Google+ kao društvenu mrežu). Skoro svaki dan se iznenadim vrteći standardne komande za update-ovanje sistema u Terminal-u otkrivajući nove mogućnosti koje mi ovaj operativni sistem pruža.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kombinacija prelijepog minimalističkog izgleda, ogromna količina dostupnog softvera, lakoća prilagođavanja sitnih problema koji me muče, lakoća pronalaska rješenja za probleme sa kojima se susrećem, odlična zajednica i fantastičan izgled (nešto što se ne može dovoljno puta naglasiti) su bila dobitna kombinacija za mene. Sada stojim u potpunosti iza elementary projekta, finansijski ih podržavam kad god sam u mogućnosti, i preporučujem elementary projekat svakom prilikom na koju naletim, pa tako i sa ovim postom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nisam počeo da pišem ovaj post sa ciljem da vas nagovorim da pređete na elementary (mada, naravno, jedna preokrenuta duša za mene znači mnogo). Smatram da je odabir prave distribucije proces sa kojim se svaki potencijalni Linuksaš sam treba suočiti i istražiti mnoge opcije prije nego što se odluči za konačno rješenje. Ovaj post pišem čisto iz razloga da navedem neke razloge zašto je elementary OS savršen operativni sistem za mene.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Dronovi - moja perspektiva</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/politics/2014/10/16/dronovi-moja-perspektiva/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-16T12:47:39+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/politics/2014/10/16/dronovi-moja-perspektiva</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dakle u zadnje vrijeme se digla tolika frka oko dronova da sam jednostavno morao da im posvetim prostora na svom blogu. Postaju dio naše svakodnevnice, u mom gradu već ima jedan i imao sam prilike izbliza da vidim kako tačno funkcioniše.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Svi smo već upoznati sa incidentom sa dronom na utakmici između Srbije i Albanije, a evo prije nekoliko minuta sam otkrio da će dronovi da budu i na današnjoj vojnoj paradi u Srbiji.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Da počnemo sa tim šta su dronovi. Većina nas je nekad tokom našeg života imala priliku da vidi automobil ili neki letjeći objekat na daljinsko upravljanje. E pa dronovi su upravo to, igračkice na daljinsko upravljanje koje hodaju nebom, imaju malo veći domet nego što smo navikli da imamo u igračkama i koštaju mnogo skuplje. Pa zašto se digla tolika frka oko njih?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dronovi mogu da imaju razne svrhe, od onih vojnih u kojima vojni službenici mogu da ih koriste da bi bombardovali mete, bio razlog za to opravdan ili ne, do snimanja nekog događaja iz ptičje perspektive. Naravno, dronovima može da upravlja samo onaj koji u rukama drži daljinski upravljač, tako da postoji šansa da ih upravljaju tako da proviruju kroz prozore vašeg kupatila dok se tuširate ili slično,  u zavisnosti od toga šta njegov vlasnik smatra zanimljivim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shvatio sam da su dronovi dio naše sadašnjice i budućnosti kada sam vidio &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=f4WGhr9V_dI&quot;&gt;video snimak na YouTube-u&lt;/a&gt; u kome je moj kvart (a i mnogo veći dio grada) snimljen iz ptičje perspektive. Prva reakcija mi je bila da je tako nešto nedopustivo, ali kada sam malo bolje pogledao snimak shvatio sam da snimak izgleda predivno, jedinstveno i nešto što nikada prije nijedna tehnologija nije uspjela da mi omogući. Pošto sam veliki frik što se tiče privatnosti, kroz glavu mi je prošla ideja da bih vjerovatno pokušao da ga skinem da sam bio svjestan da se moj kvart snima i da sam bio upoznat sa time, iako nikakvog govora o invaziji na moju privatnost nije bilo u spomenutom videu. Na tome se sve završilo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kasnije sam sa istim dronom imao neka daljnja iskustva, počevši od toga da su iz ptičje perspektive &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=_2e5HqrjJBA&quot;&gt;mnogo bolje prikazane posljedice poplava u mom gradu&lt;/a&gt;, pa sve do toga dok nisam upoznao vlasnika drona i po prvi put ga vidio uživo tokom jednog događaja u kome su video snimci snimljeni dronom pomogli da se snimi &lt;a href=&quot;http://vimeo.com/100238916&quot;&gt;ovaj video&lt;/a&gt; u kome je sumiran cijeli dvodnevni događaj. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Na tom događaju sam imao priliku da radim i dron je stavljen na svega tridesetak centimetara od mojih nogu. Neću da lažem i prizaću da mi je u nekoliko navrata palo na pamet to da ga nagazim nogom i da ga na taj način onesposobim, međutim suzdržao sam se od toga shvativši koliki je to finansijski udar na džep i da zapravo može da donese toliko novih i pozitivnih načina za korištenje.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Zaključak&lt;/em&gt;: Dronovi su dio naše sadašnjosti i naše budućnosti. Mogu da se koriste u razne svrhe. Neke od njih su vrlo pozitivne, a neke vrlo negativne. I dalje ne postoje regulacije o njihovom korištenju i poznavajući državu u kojoj živim potrajaće još nekoliko godina dok se regulative ne donesu. Jedino što možemo da uradimo trenutno jeste da vjerujemo da ih oni koji ih posjeduju koriste u dobrim svrhama. O da, ako imate viška para u džepu, svakako kupite jedan. Doživićete mnoge zanimljive situacije u njihovom korišćenju.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Donacijama možemo da napravimo razliku</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///linux/2014/10/15/donacijama-mozemo-da-napravimo-razliku/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-15T20:21:51+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//linux/2014/10/15/donacijama-mozemo-da-napravimo-razliku</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NAPOMENA: Ovo je stariji članak. Objavljen je u &lt;a href=&quot;https://libre.lugons.org/&quot;&gt;LiBRE! magazinu&lt;/a&gt; u 16. broju. Članak prenosim u cjelosti kao takav bez ikakvih izmjena. Ukoliko vas zanimaju članci na ovu temu svakako preporučujem da prelistate &lt;a href=&quot;https://libre.lugons.org/index.php/preuzimanje-pdf-hd-izdanja/&quot;&gt;LiBRE! arhivu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mi smo kao ljudska rasa dosad napravili velike korake – u pogrešnom smeru. Da, napravili smo računare, internet, otišli na mjesec, izlečili poneku bolest… Imamo mi tih nekoliko dobrih stvari koje smo napravili i uradili. A sa druge strane? Nuklearne, hidrogene i druge vrste bombi, terorizam, svaki pedalj zemlje je pod nečijim vlasništvom, svaki komad prirode je pod nečijim vlasništvom, ropstvo (i ono staromodno i ovo novo u 21. veku kada jednostavno cele dane radiš za nečiji drugi profit i jedva preživljavaš), dečja pornografija i tako dalje. Prisvojili smo sebi čitav svet jednostavno. Iako živimo sa ogromnim brojem drugih životinjskih i biljnih vrsta, nema tog dijela zemlje koji nije u vlasništvu ili neke osobe, ili neke korporacije, ili neke države. Čak smo i Antarktik uspjeli podijeliti među sobom onoliko koliko ga možemo iskoristiti – za ostatak naravno nikoga nije briga (svejedno će se istopiti u skorijoj budućnosti).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moram priznati da je ovo fascinirajuće. Dobili smo čitavu jednu planetu (zapravo ukrali od svih drugih biljnih i životinjskih vrsta, ali nećemo u detalje) da se množimo, gradimo, rušimo, iskorišćavamo… a jedina stvar koja je u 2013. još uvijek slobodna jeste nešto što smo sami napravili – internet. Zašto je tako? Pa odgovor je dosta jednostavan, zato što ne pripada nikome i zato što je odavno prešao tu granicu kada može da bude pod nečijom kontrolom. Svako ima pravo da radi šta hoće i kad hoće na njemu, niko ga ne kontroliše, niko korisniku ništa ne brani da posećuje, niko mu neće pokucati na vrata zbog nekoliko klikova… dobro, to je bilo prije nekoliko godina, i zanimljivo je koliko se toga promjenilo u pet do deset godina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U kakvom stanju je internet danas? Pa dobro, još uvek je on na neki način slobodno mjesto, ali je na dobrom putu da i on postane nečije vlasništvo. Imamo na jednoj strani ljude koji su obični korisnici i koji rade sasvim obične radnje za današnje vreme na njemu: pričaju sa prijateljima, skidaju muziku, gledaju filmove, čitaju vesti i to je manje više to. Daleko od toga da ne postoje ljudi koji rade još mnogo više od ovoga na internetu, ali su takvi ljudi ipak manjina. Sa druge strane… pa sa druge strane stoje vlade (pre svega Američka, ali ne zaostaje za njom ni vlada Velike Britanije, Nemačke i Holandije), Holivud, Silikonska dolina i svako drugi koji očekuje da će ostvariti profit od nečega što je ništa drugo nego pravilno poredan zbir nula i jedinica. Takva računica jednostavno nije moguća bez potpune kontrole. Nule i jedinice se lako kopiraju u tom istom redosledu i imamo kopiju tog istog proizvoda koji možemo proslediti dalje, nešto što se ne može sa recimo hranom, pićem, računarima… Dakle očekivati da se zaradi nešto prodavanjem jednog istog zbira nula i jedinica različitim korisnicima koji sami mogu sa tim zbirom da rade kakve god radnje požele (uključujući i kopiranje) jeste sasvim nerealno za očekivati i jednostavno nemoguće za ostvariti. Zato smo došli u vreme kada imamo DMCA tužbe svakodnevno i kada Google i Microsoft uklanjaju milione rezultata pretraga zato što krše autorska prava, a neke od tih cenzura su čak i protiv programa sa otvorenim kodom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rešenje?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Umesto da forsiramo ovakve načine za poslovanje, potrebno je napraviti mnogo jednostavnije rešenje za naplaćivanje: donacije. Sa jedne strane bi tada imali korporacije koje bi zapošljavale programere da naprave što bolji proizvod da bi korisnici baš njega koristili, a taj proizvod im se mora dosta svideti da bi mu donirali nešto (dakle mora biti ispravan, bez bug-ova, brz, pouzdan, grafički lep i da odradi posao kako treba). Sa druge strane bismo imali obične korisnike koji mogu da pristupaju svemu što požele, a to ne smatram pogubnim za proizvođače. Još nisam upoznao osobu koja ne bi pogledala neki film u kinu umesto na laptopu. Još nisam upoznao osobu koja bi se bunila da poseti koncert autora za koga je čuo preko interneta i svidela mu se. Još nisam upoznao ni osobu koja ne bi platila određenu količinu novca autoru da dobije čvrstu kopiju onoga što mu proizvođač nudi (tipa neki program, film ili muziku na CD-u ili USB-u). Dakle imamo alternativan način zarade i u primeni je u dosta manjih firmi u današnje vreme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Šta bismo sve dobili time?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kao prov kvalitetnije proizvode i proizvođače te zadovoljnije korisnike. Dobili bi novu kreativnu radnu snagu jer bi sigurno postojao neko od nas ko bi pokušao da bude deo u snimanju nekog filma ili bi pokušao da snimi pesmu kada bi jednostavno mogao da dobije program preko kojeg bi mogao to da uradi, a da ne mora da plati za takav program nekoliko stotina ili čak i nekoliko hiljada dolara. Naučna dostignuća bi bila mnogo veća kada bi svi naučnici mogli da imaju sve informacije koje im trebaju na raspolaganju dvadeset četiri sata u danu svakog dana. Verovatno ne bi napredovala isključivo jedna firma ili isključivo jedna država – čitava ljudska zajednica bi napredovala, ovaj put u pravom smeru.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Šta bismo izgubili?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U početku bi verovatno bio manji profit kada bi se više ljudi okrenulo ovom načinu zarade, međutim ako bi privukli više ljudi i napravili kvalitetan proizvod, ne vidim razlog zašto se za taj proizvod ne bi donirala velika količina novca. Dakle, u početku bi takve firme izgubile deo svog novca. Ali moramo se zapitati šta je postao novac u današnje vrijeme? Ništa drugo nego još jedan zbir pravilno poslaganih nula i jedinica.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Šta mogu ja kao pojedinac da uradim?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovaj korak jeste vrlo jednostavan, ali smo u takvom vremenu kada bi taj jedan ispravan korak danas doneo mnogo lepše sutra kada je tehnologija u pitanju – doniraj. Mnogo ljudi jednostavno nije svesno da za skoro svaki program postoji neka besplatna alternativa. Možda nije bolja ili brža ili grafički privlačnija od drugih komercijalnih proizvoda, ali ne smeš da zaboraviš da su ti proizvodi lošiji samo zato što njegovi autori nisu u dovoljnoj meri podržani od strane običnog korisnika. Dakle, umesto da platiš 150 dolara na neki XYZ program će ti služiti za određeni posao kao što si imao u planu, doniraj 100 dolara nekom ZYX programu koji ima slične mogućnosti i možda je za stepenicu niži od tog komercijalnog. Na taj način ćeš dobiti program sa kojim ćeš se morati verovatno malo potruditi i napraviti tri klika umesto dva, ali daćeš svoju podršku nekim dobrim programerima koji su se potrudili da ti pruže tu tehnologiju i još će ti ostati 50 dolara u džepu. Kada bi dobar deo nas tako postupao, imali bi neviđene koristi, i kao pojedinci, i kao zajednica, a komercijalni programi bi postepeno mogli nestaju u potpunosti, muzika bi se sve više davala besplatno, a možda bismo tokom naših života doživeli i da možemo da gledamo neke filmove bez straha da nam policija zbog toga pokuca na vrata. Dakle sve što je potrebno je napraviti jedan korak u suprotnom smeru od onoga na koji smo navikli.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Koje softverske firme vas kontrolišu?</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/human%20hacking/linux/2014/10/15/koje-softverske-firme-vas-kontrolisu/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-15T19:55:07+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/human%20hacking/linux/2014/10/15/koje-softverske-firme-vas-kontrolisu</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NAPOMENA: Ovaj blog post sam napisao prije mnogo vremena (dovoljno daleko da bude stariji od ideje da uopšte napravim blog). Sve do sada nije objavljen nigdje, a sada sam dobio želju da ga podijelim sa javnošću i na taj način malo popunim svoj blog. Post je ostao neizmijenjen u cjelosti i kao takav kopiran iz LibreOffice-a, tako da su podaci malo stariji a stil pisanja takav kakav jeste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U zadnja dva mjeseca smo stalno bombardovani činjenicama da postoji neko ko upravlja svime što radimo na internetu. Od toga da mogu da skupljaju metapodatke o našim pozivima i SMS porukama, preko toga da čitaju naše mejlove, Facebook razgovore, objave na Twitter-u i aktivnosti na Youtube-u. Podaci koje smo saznali u zadnja dva mjeseca nam daju do znanja da negdje postoji računar koji zna više o nama od naših prijatelja, porodice, pa čak i od nas samih. Mi ne znamo šta smo pretraživali po Google-u prije godinu dana u ovo vrijeme, ali postoji neki računar u svijetu koji to zna. Moguće je čak i da postoji više računara koji to znaju. Recimo, jedan u Google-ovoj korporaciji, drugi u NSA kojem je Google dostavio te informacije, treći na teritoriji naše države koji su na neki način pokupili te informacije od prethodna dva računara a četvrti negdje od strane nekoga ko je uspjeo da se dokopa informacija sa bilo kojeg od prethodna tri računara. Ovo je samo pretpostavka, ali ne čini se toliko nemoguća, zar ne?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Odavno je već rečeno da ako ništa ne plaćate za neki servis, vi sami ste produkat. To je već odavno činjenica u svijetu računara i interneta. Primjer: ne plaćate gmail korisnički račun, gledanje videa na YouTube-u i ne plaćate pretrage preko Google-ove tražilice, ali gledate reklame, što je jednostavan način da oni zarade na vama. Sada ću vam dokazati da postoji ne samo jedna, nego nekoliko firmi koje vas u potpunosti kontrolišu.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google vas kontroliše. Svjestan sam kakvu izjavu sam dao i stojim iza nje. Uzmimo tipičnog korisnika, recimo da se zove Marko. Marko ima smartphone sa Android operativnim sistemom. Taj sistem je Google-ov produkt. Preko njega će pretraživati nešto po internetu. Koristiće za to Google-ovu tražilicu. Recimo da želi da objavi video, na kojem će to servisu uraditi? Na YouTube-u, još jednom Google-ovom servisu. Da bi objavio video, mora da napravi korisnički račun, a pošto YouTube ne dozvoljava niti jednu drugu mejl adresu, mora da napravi gmail adresu. Ne pričam o sitnim radnjama, pričam o radnjama koje radi milijarda ljudi svakoga dana. Google vas jednostavno kontroliše. Mnogi ne mogu da zamisle niti dan bez njegovih servisa, zar ne? A nisam niti spomenuo Google Chrome, Chrome OS, Google Calendar i ostalo. Čak i kada je njihov mali servis kao što je bio Google Reader nestao nastala je pometnja, šta bi se tek desilo sa većinom nas kada bi nestao čitav Google?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft vas kontroliše. Microsoft nije ništa bolji od Google-a. Recimo da uzmete neki laptop koji vam se sviđa, platite nekoliko stotina ili čak i hiljada eura za njega. Uz njega dođe Windows 8. Da li ga možete koristiti odma? Ne. Morate se prijaviti. Da bi se prijavili, morate napraviti Outlook korisnički račun. Praktički nećete moći pristupiti vašem laptopu od hiljadu eura bez pravljenja Outlook adrese. Jedini način da to uradite jeste da označite da imate poteškoće sa internetom prilikom podešavanja koje se pojavljuju pri samom dizanju sistema i tu ćete dobiti sasvim malu opciju da napravite lokalni korisnički račun za Windows. Većina korisnika vjerovatno ni ne zna za tu opciju, a u Windows 9, ako ne već i u Windows 8.1 operativnom sistemu čak će i ta mala i trenutno sakrivena opcija vjerovatno da nestane. Windows i dalje zauzima ogroman dio tržišta kada su desktop računari i laptopi u pitanju, nekih 80% recimo (ovo je samo pretpostavka), svi će postepeno preći na Windows 8. Možda kada izađe Windows 9, možda tek kada izađe Windows 10, ali hoće, isto kao što su svi prešli na Windows XP. E sada, po mom iskustvu sa Windows 8, ljepši je, brži je, troši manje baterije na laptopu i ima neke fantastične aplikacije – besplatne. Naravno, besplatne su samo na prvi pogled, jer većina aplikacija (čak i one koje dolaze sa samim sistemom) prikazuje reklame. Dakle, nije im dosta stotinu-dvije dolara koje su uzeli od vas kad ste kupili sam računar/laptop i još vas natjerali da napravite njegovu mejl adresu čak i ako je niste željeli, već vas i sam sistem bombarduje reklamama. Postoje i neke besplatne Xbox igre za njega, ali naravno, i one su pune reklama osim ako ne uplatite malu količinu novca na njihov račun. Poslije toga, da bi uživali u tim igrama ili omogućili neke dodatne nivoe, opet morate platiti. Ne zaboravimo i biznis koji se odvija preko Microsoft-ovog Office paketa koji opet košta nekoliko stotina dolara. Dakle, Microsoft vas kontroliše.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Facebook vas kontroliše. Facebook je mnogo drugačiji od dvije prethodne firme. Facebook nema više servisa, ima samo jedan. Ali, na tom jednom servisu vršite komunikaciju sa svim vašim prijateljima, pa čak i ljudima koje ne znate. Stavljate lične fotografije, stavljate fotografije prijatelja, ponekad i neki video zaluta, događaji, aplikacije, fan stranice, grupe… Da se ne lažemo, Facebook nije uopšte loš servis, samo ga većina ljudi ne koristi kako treba. Kao posljedica toga, Facebook ima sve o nama, od imena i prezimena, preko broja telefona, slika i videa, pa sve do dokaza o skoro svim postupcima koje smo uradili u zadnjih par godina. Neke od njih nisu legalne, a zbog nekih ne bi nikada izašli iz kuće od srama kad bi izašli u javnost. Ali kada malo bolje razmislimo, sve ovo već jeste u javnosti, sve se ovo već krije negdje na nekim serverima u SAD-u hiljadama kilometara udaljenim. Većina nas te servere nikada nije vidjela čak niti na slici, a opet smo dovoljno glupi da im povjerimo sve moguće informacije o nama. Dakle strancima smo dali sve informacije koje nikada ne bismo voljeli da dođu ni do naših najbližih, a kamoli do nekog stranca?&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slična priča se ponavlja i sa Apple-om, mada nisam dovoljno upoznat sa njihovim proizvodima da bih mogao da napišem malu priču o tome kao što sam uradio sa ove tri firme. Istina jeste da mi više jednostavno nemamo kontrolu nad svojim podacima. Istina jeste da ne trebamo stavljati naše podatke u cloud servise koje vode nepoznate kompanije na nepoznatim serverima. Istina jeste da trebamo uzmati naše podatke nazad sa takvih stranih servisa koje nude strane kompanije u stranim državama na serverima koje ni na slici nismo vidjeli niti jednom u svom životu niti znamo nekoga ko je vidjeo te servere. Trebamo da razvijemo decentralizovane sisteme. Trebamo da vratimo naše podatke nama, i tada, i samo tada ćemo biti sigurni da nam ih niko neće ukrasti, niti vlada, niti neke korporacije. Trebamo voditi sami svoje servere i razmjenjivati podatke sa osobama sa kojima vjerujemo – i samo sa njima.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Da li živimo u cyberpunk svetu?</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/linux/2014/10/15/da-li-zivimo-u-cyberpunk-svetu/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-15T19:51:45+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/linux/2014/10/15/da-li-zivimo-u-cyberpunk-svetu</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NAPOMENA: Ovaj blog post sam napisao prije mnogo vremena (dovoljno daleko da bude stariji od ideje da uopšte napravim blog). Sve do sada nije objavljen nigdje, a sada sam dobio želju da ga podijelim sa javnošću i na taj način malo popunim svoj blog. Post je ostao neizmijenjen u cjelosti i kao takav kopiran iz LibreOffice-a, tako da su podaci malo stariji a stil pisanja takav kakav jeste.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Inspirisan izvrsnim člankom koji je izašao u regionalnom portalu Linux Za Sve &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.linuxzasve.com/floss-kao-mainstream-da-ali-pod-kojim-uvjetima&quot;&gt;koji možete pročitati ovde&lt;/a&gt;, ne mogu da se ne zapitam koliko smo blizu jednoj izjavi iznesenoj u tom članku. Ta izjava glasi:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;„[FLOSS zajednica] je jedan od bitnih ključeva za spas modernog društva, koje je opasno zaglibilo u materijalizam i koje nije daleko od kaotične cyberpunk anarhije.“&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ta usporedba današnjeg sveta sa cyberpunk anarhijom kakvu sam kao i većina nas nekoliko puta video u filmovima (Matrix, Blade Runner…) i „doživeo“ u PC igrama (Remember Me) me je zaintrigirala. Za one koji nisu upoznati (ako postoje takve osobe), osnova cyberpunk priče je da će u budućnosti postojati neka totalitaristička kompanija/organizacija koja će upravljati ljudima i tehnologijom na koji god način žele i da niko neće moći da ih zaustavi. Bez te kompanije/organizacije nećemo moći da preživimo jer ćemo postati direktno ovisni o njoj, žrtvujući sve što imamo da bi dobili njene proizvode, a ta kompanija/organizacija će o nama znati više od nas samih. Što više razmišljam o tome, sve više razumem da nas to ne čeka u budućnosti. Budućnost je već stigla. &lt;strong&gt;Mi smo deo cyberpunk sveta.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovaj cyberpunk svet se u nekoj meri razlikuje od one priče koju smo gledali na filmovima, ali suština je ista. Cyberpunk svet nije zavladao u stvarnosti, ali jeste u virtualnom svetu. Prosečan korisnik danas provodi većinu svoga vremena u tom virtualnom svetu. Prosečan korisnik nije ovisan o samo jednom proizvodu jedne kompanije. Ovisan je o nekoliko njih. Prije nego što kažem svoje mišljenje želim samo da navedem &lt;a href=&quot;www.netmarketshare.com&quot;&gt;ovu stranicu&lt;/a&gt; kao izvor podataka koje ću trenutno da izložim. Podaci vrede za avgust 2013. godine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;91,19% korisnika desktopa i laptopa koristi neku verziju Microsoft-ovog operativnog sistema.
70,98% korisnika interneta koristi Google kao njihov pretraživač.
15% svih ljudi koji trenutno žive na svijetu posjeduje Facebook profil.
Preko 15% svih ljudi koji trenutno žive na svijetu posjećuje YouTube bar jednom mjesečno.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dakle u osnovi imamo tri kompanije o kojima je prosečan čovek ovisan: Microsoft, Google i Facebook. Da li je tu kraj? Naravno da ne. Postoji i NSA, organizacija koja sigurno sakuplja podatke koje korisnici ostave na 10 od 20 najposećenijih stranica na svetu (&lt;a href=&quot;www.alexa.com/topsites&quot;&gt;prema ovim izvorima&lt;/a&gt;). Dakle stvari nisu baš kompletno kao na filmu, ali su dovoljno blizu da se zapitamo šta je sledeće. Ogromna količina korisnika neće ni da čuje za operativni sistem koji nije razvijen od strane Microsoft-a. Ogromna količina korisnika neće ni da pokuša da koristi neki drugi pretraživač osim već onih dobro poznatih kao što su Google, Yahoo i Bing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pitate se kada ćemo da živimo u cyberpunk svetu? Shvatite da smo već njegov deo. Naravno, ništa od ovoga trenutno nije obavezno i još uvek imamo pravo na slobodan izbor. Ali, da budemo iskreni, taj izbor koristi toliko malen broj ljudi da je zanemarljiv. Sada je samo pitanje kada ćemo mi koji pripadamo tom malom broju ljudi početi da budemo proganjani zbog toga i kada će celo stanovništvo biti čipovano tako da nam se prati svaki korak.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Broadening my perspective</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/2014/10/05/broadening-my-perspective/"/>
   <updated>2014-10-05T13:32:11+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/2014/10/05/broadening-my-perspective</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This blog is about to go into completely different direction. Don’t get me wrong, I still love Linux, I still use it regularly. I’m still a big FLOSS enthusiast and I still want to be a security expert. That won’t change as long as I’m alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, there’s a lot more going on in my life and I want to express myself in a lot bigger way. I’m going to try to categorize my posts properly so you could filter them out just the way you want it, but I’m going to be writing about lots of stuff here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what else will you be able to find in my blog in the near future? Well, there would be a lot of posts about human psychology, music and my personal life. You’ll see me develop as a person professionally AND mentally. I have a couple of blog posts almost ready to go, so stay tuned!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Ubuntu utopija #budiUbuntu</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///linux/2014/08/18/ubuntu-utopija-budiubuntu/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-18T03:25:38+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//linux/2014/08/18/ubuntu-utopija-budiubuntu</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Postoji nešto što nas izdvaja iznad miliona i miliona drugih vrsta koje su živile nekada u istoriji naše planete: snalažljivi smo i držimo se zajedno.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naravno, to držanje zajedno je često narušeno. Svake godine desetine hiljada ljudi izgubi svoj život raspravljajući se oko nekog mitskog bića za koje ne možemo da potvrdimo niti da postoji niti da ne postoji. Ljubomora nas čini užasnim osobama. Imamo različite poroke i u zavisnosti od tih poroka radimo neke užasne stvari.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ali, kada upoznamo osobu bez da joj znamo spol, boju kože, religijska uvjerenja i godine, nevjerovatne stvari se događaju. Jednom kada se udaljimo od osnovnih predrasuda koje su sastavni dio svakoga od nas, postajemo dio zajednice, a ta zajednica je sposobna da uradi mnogo toga. To smo dokazali tokom poplava koje su ove godine pogodile naša područja. To dokazujemo svake godine protestima širom svijeta i na još bezbroj primjera. Odbacimo predrasude i postanimo dio zajednice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biti ubuntu znači biti dio zajednice. Biti ubuntu znači biti dio nečega većeg od nas. Biti ubuntu znači pomagati jedni drugima. Biti ubuntu znači uzimati od zajednice, ali joj u istoj mjeri i vraćati nazad. Biti ubuntu znači biti slobodan. Biti ubuntu znači biti srećan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Može se smatrati da je čitava Linux zajednica nastala na ovim principima. Međutim, Ubuntu zajednica je najrasprostranjenija. Kao takva, učinili smo mnogo toga. Kreirali smo &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ubuntu.com/download/desktop&quot;&gt;najpopularniju Linux distribuciju&lt;/a&gt;, kreirali smo jednostavno &lt;a href=&quot;http://elementaryos.org/&quot;&gt;prelijepu Linux distribuciju&lt;/a&gt;, kreirali smo Linux &lt;a href=&quot;http://linuxmint.com/&quot;&gt;distribucije za početnike&lt;/a&gt;, kreirali smo nekoliko korisničkih okruženja, odličan menadžer paketa, distribucije &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.backbox.org/&quot;&gt;za ispitivanje penetracije&lt;/a&gt;, distribucije &lt;a href=&quot;http://edubuntu.com/&quot;&gt;za edukaciju korisnika&lt;/a&gt;, naš softver se koristi &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.muenchen.de/rathaus/Stadtverwaltung/Direktorium/LiMux.html&quot;&gt;u državnim institucijama&lt;/a&gt;, prilagođeni smo &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.educa.madrid.org/web/madrid_linux/&quot;&gt;školama&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://ubuntustudio.org/&quot;&gt;umjetnicima&lt;/a&gt;, drugačijim jezicima…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Iz jednog projekta su nastale desetine odličnih projekata, svaki sa svojom posebnom namjenom i svaki na svoj način važan za zajednicu. Sve smo to omogućili držeći se ubuntu principa. Zašto ne bi i ti? Odbaci predrasude, uzmi prazan DVD i istraži sa nama ubuntu utopiju.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovaj post je moj drugi doprinos &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?&amp;amp;q=%23budiUbuntu&quot;&gt;#budiUbuntu&lt;/a&gt; akciji. Moj prvi doprinos &lt;a href=&quot;http://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/08/18/moj-put-od-fedore-preko-archa-do-ubuntu-derivata-budiubuntu/&quot;&gt;se nalazi ovdje&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Moj put od Fedore preko Archa do Ubuntu derivata #budiUbuntu</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///linux/2014/08/18/moj-put-od-fedore-preko-archa-do-ubuntu-derivata-budiubuntu/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-18T02:44:10+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//linux/2014/08/18/moj-put-od-fedore-preko-archa-do-ubuntu-derivata-budiubuntu</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dakle, kao i svaka osoba na ovoj planeti, prije nešto više od godinu dana sam počeo biti bombardovan sa člancima o vijestima koje nam donosi &lt;em&gt;zviždač&lt;/em&gt; (eng. whistleblower) Edward Snowden. Saznao sam koliko je NSA duboko zavukla nos u naše guzice. Otprilike u isto vrijeme sam završio srednju školu te samim tim imao ogromnu količinu slobodnog vremena. To vrijeme sam iskoristio da bih se fokusirao na mrežnu sigurnost. Studirajući inženjersku informatiku znao sam da ću prije ili kasnije morati da se odlučim za neki dio računarstva koji me najviše zanima, a oduvijek me fascinirala sigurnost u moderno doba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I tako, malo povučen od strane Snowdena i ljudi koji su na redditu pomagali jedni drugima da izbjegnu nadzor od strane NSA, malo povučen željom da naučim što više mogu o sigurnosti u digitalnom dobu, naletih na to čudo zvano Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Odma u početku mog Linuxaškog puta, ljudi su me odvajali od Ubuntua govoreći mi da Canonical nije ništa bolji od Microsofta, da ni Ubuntu derivati nisu ništa bolji što se tiče privatnosti, da Ubuntu koristi neka stara softverska rješenja u sklopu svog sistema i slične stvari, međutim u tom trenutku moj put kroz Linux je bio neizbježan. Počeo je sa Fedorom pa me odveo sve do Arch Linuxa u to doba.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U svakom od isprobanih ne-Ubuntu slučajeva pojavljivalo se nešto što mi je falilo, neki program, neka funkcija, nešto što bi me zadržalo na njemu više nego na crackovanom Prozoru sa kojim sam napravio dual boot. Kao malo razvijeniji početnik u Linux svijetu, moj propast sa Arch Linuxom je bio neizbježan, te sam se nakon njega odvojio od Linux svijeta na neko vrijeme, ostavljajući raspadnut sistem za sobom i kriveći AMD zbog njihove užasne podrške za vlasničke drajvere na Linux platformi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nekoliko mjeseci kasnije naletio sam na jednu novu distribuciju koja mi je zapala za oko: elementary OS Luna. Prelijepo dizajnirana, troši minimalno resursa, stane na običan CD (čime se malo koja distribucija današnjice može pohvaliti)… Instalirao sam ga i po prvi put postao dio Ubuntu zajednice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sistem je prelijep i i dalje je moj glavni izbor što se tiče distribucije. Sve probleme na koje sam našao sam uspješno riješio. Ukoliko mi DuckDuckGo pretraga, koja je obično uključivala kratak opis problema i riječ elementary, nije pomogla, obično bih samo zamijenio riječ elementary sa riječi Ubuntu i našao bih rješenje svog problema. Uz odličan Ubuntu repozitorij i prelijep elementary izgled osjećao sam se izvanredno i moj procenat korištenja Linuxa ispred Prozora se popeo sa 20 na 70 posto vremena provedenog za laptopom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Prošlo je već pola 2014. godine i elementary OS Luna je odavno postao zastareo sistem. Ubuntu 14.04 je već odavno izašao, kao i većina derivata baziranih na njemu, međutim novi elementary se još uvijek zvao Isis i čekao ga je dalek put do svoje beta verzije. Vođen prethodnim pozitivnim iskustvom sa lakoćom rješavanja problema na elementary derivatu, pokušavam Ubuntu, GNOME Ubuntu i na kraju se odlučujem za Kubuntu osjećajući se pomalo nostalgično za KDE interfejsom koji me je doveo u Linux svijet i koji sam koristio u svakoj distribuciji prije instalacije Lune. Ovaj punokrvni KDE sistem mi je pružio sve što sam ikada trebao i njegov korganizer softver je nešto što sam mjesecima bezuspješno tražio na svom Prozoru. Moje vrijeme provedeno na Linux platformi se sada već povećalo na 90%, koristeći Prozore samo kada trebam da pokrenem neke virtualne mašine ili imam potrebu da se malo opustim uz World of Tanks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;elementary OS je u međuvremenu promjenio ime u Freya te je izašla prva beta verzija. Vođen prethodnim pozitivnim iskustvom sa oba Ubuntu derivata (elementary kao ljepoticom i Kubuntuom kao punokrvnim sistemom koji ima sve što trebam), po prvi put kreiram trostruki boot i osjećam se savršeno sa svoja dva ljubimca: Freyom i Kubuntuom. Razmišljao sam o tome da im dam neka posebna imena kao što &lt;a href=&quot;http://savesna.wordpress.com/2014/06/17/tosa-mali-al-ubuntu-udoban/&quot;&gt;Savesna&lt;/a&gt; svoj računar naziva Toše, ali sama imena distribucija mi se čine savršena, tako da se sa ponosom predstavljam internetu kao Kubuntaš i elementaš.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ovaj post je moj doprinos &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?&amp;amp;q=%23budiUbuntu&quot;&gt;#budiUbuntu&lt;/a&gt; akciji. Ovom prilikom bih se zahvalio &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.milosmiladinovic.com/2014/06/ubuntu-filozofija-nacin-zivota-koji-inspirise-budiubuntu/&quot;&gt;Milošu Miladinoviću na pokretanju ideje&lt;/a&gt;. Vrlo vjerovatno u vrlo kratkom vremenu od objavljivanja ovog teksta slijedi još jedan o Ubuntu filozofiji čime ću da upotpunim svoj doprinos &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/search?&amp;amp;q=%23budiUbuntu&quot;&gt;#budiUbuntu&lt;/a&gt; akciji.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Reading Mission Accomplished!</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/2014/08/14/reading-mission-accomplished/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-14T06:05:17+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/2014/08/14/reading-mission-accomplished</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, somewhere around the Middle of June I set a goal to myself: read three books by the end of August. And I did it! I’ve read three books so far and I’m planning on reading another one as soon as I get a hold of some book that I find interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I kinda feel fascinated by George R. R. Martin. I’ve read the first part of A Song of Ice and Fire and I knew I wanted to read more of his books. So, book fair was organized in my city and I immediately ran over there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got enough money to buy two books. I &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; probably buy even more books if I was looking for some cheap books and I didn’t knew what I was looking for, but I knew exactly what I was looking for: books by George R. R. Martin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, immediately, I bought a second part of A Song of Ice and Fire series and I found this other book by him called The Armageddon Rag. I bought both of them and two or three weeks later, I finished reading both of them. It feels so damn amazing!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Books are amazing! J&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>WhyMicrosoft.com - The Worst Marketing Site Ever?</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///linux/2014/08/10/67/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-10T16:38:28+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//linux/2014/08/10/67</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Browsing through a &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/u/0/communities/109586015108702871702&quot;&gt;Google+ group&lt;/a&gt; dedicated to Linux users in Serbia and Balkan region, I saw a post that linked a web page called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.whymicrosoft.com/&quot;&gt;Why Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be honest, I’m &lt;a href=&quot;http://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/08/05/confession-microsoft-is-not-so-bad/&quot;&gt;not a Microsoft hater&lt;/a&gt; even though I use &lt;a href=&quot;http://kubuntu.org/&quot;&gt;Kubuntu Linux distribution&lt;/a&gt; as my primary operating system. I’ve decided to check out that site just to see why Microsoft thinks their products are so much better than competitors products.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I took a few screenshots and I want to present to you Microsoft’s marketing strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[gallery ids=”68,69,70,71,72,73”]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see in the pictures, Microsoft’s strategy consists on deceiving users by comparing their software’s compatibility with &lt;em&gt;their software&lt;/em&gt;, some lies and some double standards.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Cloud Wars from a Consumer Perspective</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/2014/08/09/cloud-wars-from-a-consumer-perspective/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-09T16:22:10+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/2014/08/09/cloud-wars-from-a-consumer-perspective</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, I’ve got two primary cloud providers: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.mail.ru/&quot;&gt;Mail.ru cloud&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://onedrive.live.com/&quot;&gt;OneDrive&lt;/a&gt;. I’ve been using both of them for quite some time. Mail.Ru cloud supports Linux and gives 100 GB for free. They’ve also had a promo action that lasted for a month and anyone who clicked on a certain link got 1 TB for free. Yup, 1 TB of cloud storage absolutely free. The only problem: the interface is in Russian. Not a big deal and once you get a hang of where things are located using the app is quite easy. They support pretty much any platform you can think of and Linux integration (tried it on Kubuntu and elementary OS) as well as Windows integration works perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, sometimes I just want to share my files with someone. I’m not sure if that is possible with Mail.Ru cloud, but I know a place where it is: Microsoft OneDrive. As I’ve explained before in &lt;a href=&quot;http://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/08/05/confession-microsoft-is-not-so-bad/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;, I’m not a big Microsoft hater even though I’m a Linux user and I trust them &lt;a href=&quot;http://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/08/08/mozilla-firefox-does-everyone-thing-of-it-just-as-an-alternative-to-chrome/&quot;&gt;far more then I trust Google&lt;/a&gt;. I have an Office 365 subscription for about a month or two and I got 20 GB of cloud storage because of that which, combining with 7 gigabytes for free
and synchronizing my Windows 8.1 sums up to 30 GB. Well, not so bad, but still, too far from 1 TB for free that I got on my other cloud service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, recently, Microsoft &lt;a href=&quot;http://mashable.com/2014/06/23/onedrive-price-cuts/&quot;&gt;lowered the price&lt;/a&gt; of their storage and I also got 1 TB for free using OneDrive thanks to my Office 365 subscription.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how to integrate OneDrive with Linux? Well, I did try to use OneDrive-D but I got a strange error which I’m not capable of fixing, so I decided to find some other solution, and I did manage to do so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The service is called Storage Made Easy, it offers free account where you can add up to three cloud providers and it supports Linux nativelly with it’s free aplication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To sum things up, I’ve got 2 TB of cloud storage by practially paying nothing, and I have no idea what the hell am I supposed to do with that much of a storage.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Ko koga špijunira u političkom vrhu BiH? (2. dio)</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///cyber%20security/politics/2014/08/08/ko-koga-spijunira-u-politickom-vrhu-bih-2-dio/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-08T22:57:55+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//cyber%20security/politics/2014/08/08/ko-koga-spijunira-u-politickom-vrhu-bih-2-dio</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Došlo je vrijeme za drugi dio članka o tome ko koga špijunira u političkom vrhu BiH. Prvi možete pročitati &lt;a href=&quot;http://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/08/07/ko-koga-spijunira-u-politickom-vrhu-bih/&quot;&gt;ovdje&lt;/a&gt;. Da skratim članak, nepoznat haker preuzeo 40ak gigabajta podataka od firme Gamma koja služi za kreiranje softvera za online špijuniranje koji se naziva FinFisher. Taj softver firma Gamma prodaje isključivo vladama, a među državama kojima je prodala softver se našla i Bosna i Hercegovina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nisam još uspio da preuzmem čitav torrent od 38,6 gigabajta podataka (trenutno je tek na 24%), tako da nisam bio ni u stanju da analiziram podatke koje preuzimam. Međutim, pomoć sam dobio od samog hakera koji je preko &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/GammaGroupPR&quot;&gt;tviter profila&lt;/a&gt; objavio link sa porukama koje su korisnici slali službi za podršku. Vrijedi pogledati, zar ne?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otvaram &lt;a href=&quot;http://pastebin.com/raw.php?i=GN9wn7xn&quot;&gt;Pastebin&lt;/a&gt; i prve poruke na koje nailazim imaju upravo Bosnu i Hercegovinu kao zemlju porijekla. Vrijeme slanja poruke je kraj maja mjeseca ove godine, dakle otprilike u isto vrijeme kada je naša država patila od poplava (samo da dam vremensku referencu).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Čitajući poruku vidim da je korisnik ostavio i svoj Skype adresu za kontakt: sanjin.custovic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Otvorio sam Skype, pretražio to ime i došao do podatka da se osoba koja se krije iza tog korisničkog imena nalazi u Sarajevu. Pronalazak IP adrese nije urodio plodom i nekoliko metoda koje sam pronašao na internetu nije uspjelo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Već sam napredovao, imamo ime, prezime, Skype profil i mjesto stanovanja jedne od osoba zaduženih za održavanje tog softvera.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Traženje po Google-u nije puno urodilo plodom, međutim jesam našao neke zanimljive podatke. Izgleda da osoba iza tog profila obožava da ostavlja komentare po forumima, tako da sam među prvim rezultatima uspio da pronađem &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.klix.ba/profil/sanjin-custovic&quot;&gt;profil na Klix.ba&lt;/a&gt; i &lt;a href=&quot;http://disqus.com/sanjincustovic/&quot;&gt;Disqus profil&lt;/a&gt;. Ne mogu da garantujem da iza njih stoji ista osoba kao i iza Skype naloga, ali komentari su svakako zanimljivi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Međutim, nešto se tu nije podudaralo. Skype-ov nalog je upućivao da boravi u Sarajevu, Facebook profil povezan sa Disqus profilom je upućivao na to da je osoba u Švedskoj zapravo, a neki &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Trojan7Sec/status/497461960121024514&quot;&gt;tvitovi&lt;/a&gt; su nekako izvukli informacije da su IP adrese prijavljivanja tog Skype profila povezale ga sa Bahrainom i Kinom. Moja predpostavka jeste da su te informacije izvukli iz dupeta, ali ajde.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Odmaknimo se malo od njegovog Skype profila i vidimo šta još imamo. Korisničko ime koje je poslalo upit glasi: OSA/OBA, što je skraćeno od &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.osa-oba.gov.ba/indexbos.htm&quot;&gt;Obavještajno-sigurnosta agencija/Obavještajno-bezbjednosna-agencija BiH&lt;/a&gt;. Generalni direktor agencije je Almir Džuvo, koji je na čelu te agencije mandat za mandatom još od osnivanja te agencije negdje 2003. godine, dakle prije 11 godina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Još par klikova i saznam par kontroverzi iza njega, poput &lt;a href=&quot;http://croportal.ba/vijesti/bih/3932-direktor-obavjetajne-slube-almir-duvo-ima-monopol-u-dravnim-institucijama&quot;&gt;ove&lt;/a&gt; i &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.javno.ba/bih/uj-i-almir-duvo-pijun.html&quot;&gt;ove&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dakle, došao sam do toga koja je agencija naručila softver, do Skype profila osobe koja je zamolila za podršku koristeći profil OSA/OBA i povezao sam to sa glavnim čovjekom agencije koji je na čelu te agencije od njenog osnivanja. Sledjeći korak: otkrivanje mogućnosti softvera i pokušaj dolaska do meta preko podataka koje preuzimam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NAPOMENA:&lt;/strong&gt; Ovo moje “istraživanje” nije pokušaj da otkrijem zloupotrebe položaja ili nešto slično. Ovo je samo pokušaj da povežem podatke javno dostupne na internetu kako bih otkrio šta se događa. Nisam &lt;em&gt;black hat&lt;/em&gt; haker, te samim tim niti jednu od informacija nisam ukrao. Sve što koristim su javno dostupne informacije.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Čim dođem do dovoljno informacija za treći dio, objavljujem na blogu.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Mozilla Firefox – Does Everyone Thing of it Just as an Alternative to Chrome?</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/2014/08/08/mozilla-firefox-does-everyone-thing-of-it-just-as-an-alternative-to-chrome/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-08T15:32:27+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/2014/08/08/mozilla-firefox-does-everyone-thing-of-it-just-as-an-alternative-to-chrome</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This is something that’s bothering me in the last 20 minutes I guess. Does really everyone think of it just as an alternative to Chrome? To be honest, Chrome is winning the browser market, Apple and Microsoft are trying to stop that, but only with one goal: replacing Chrome with their own solutions. Is there anyone who thinks that a small non-profit organization like Mozilla can do to mess that up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s step up a little. Let’s talk about operating systems. Microsoft has Windows and controls pretty much all of the desktops out there. Apple has his own Mac products. Google has most of the mobile users and Chrome OS. While Mozilla does not have anything besides Firefox OS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t get me wrong, I love Mozilla and would buy a phone with Firefox OS as soon as it becomes available in my country. But, loving Mozilla as an organization is actually pretty much any reason why someone would buy Firefox OS phone in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if you use the Internet (which of course you do, otherwise you won’t be reading this blog post) there’s like a 99,9% chance that you’re using one or more of the Google products. Google Search, YouTube, GMail, Blogger or something else. Now the problem is, if you don’t use Chrome, you have to live with some limitations while using Google’s services on the web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me give you an example. My roommate played some songs a couple of months ago using YouTube as a platform. Suddenly, he started speeding up and slowing down the playback of those songs. I was curious, how does he do that? But I didn’t say a word, I thought he downloaded those songs and messed around with their speed using his audio player. It went on for days and I realized that he’s changing songs far more quickly than he could downloaded them and played. So I took a glimpse at his laptop and saw that he’s not using anything besides his browser to do so. And, his browser, of course, was Google Chrome. Then I thought he’s using some extension that allows him to do so. So I finally got enough courage to ask him how does he do that? He said he’s not using anything besides Google Chrome. I could not believe it so I installed Chrome and I realized that he’s telling the truth. Playback speed options were there once I opened a YouTube video with Chrome. I could not believe it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So Google messed around with YouTube and I could probably remake this option just by switching my user agent in Firefox, but that was not the end. Soon I found out Google has some limitations on using Google’s Docs and other services. So Google is kind of forcing you to use Chrome to use those specific features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if Google steps up a little and starts implementing some other features specifically for Chrome? He’s going to force people to use Chrome to access those specific features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can Mozilla compete with that when Google practically controls the Internet and we’re all using their products? It can’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no way for someone to stop using Google’s services. I did try to do that. So I switched to Firefox from Chrome, I used mail.ru as my email provider, I started using DuckDuckGo as my primary search engine, but that’s as far as I could go. I can’t stop using YouTube and DuckDuckGo because even though DuckDuckGo is great, it can’t provide the perfect results to my searches so I occasionally have to enter !g bang in my search bar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we’re stuck in a wormhole. We have to use Google’s services and by doing that, we have to be ready to accept the fact that there are certain features we’re missing. And we can’t stop using Google’s services completely and enjoy browsing the Internet. It’s just not possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what I’m asking everyone to do, on the Internet &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; in real life, &lt;a href=&quot;http://robert.ocallahan.org/2014/08/choose-firefox-now-or-later-you-wont.html&quot;&gt;start using Firefox while you still have a choice&lt;/a&gt;! It looks to me like sooner or later we’re not going to have an alternative. And that really bums me out as a huge Firefox and Thunderbird fan.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Ko koga špijunira u političkom vrhu BiH?</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///cyber%20security/politics/2014/08/08/ko-koga-spijunira-u-politickom-vrhu-bih/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-08T00:27:08+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//cyber%20security/politics/2014/08/08/ko-koga-spijunira-u-politickom-vrhu-bih</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Listajući početnu na Tviteru naletio sam na nešto zanimljivo. Nepoznati haker koji se krije iza aliasa Phineas Fisher je 6. augusta hakovao stranicu koja stoji iza programa FinFisher. Taj program jeste dosta nepoznat za javnost, ali ne bi trebao da bude. Program je razvijen u Njemačkoj sa ciljem da se prodaje vladama različitih zemalja kako bi špijunirali one koje odluče da žele da špijuniraju. Haker je zatim objavio &lt;a href=&quot;https://netzpolitik.org/wp-upload/finfisher.torrent&quot;&gt;torrent&lt;/a&gt; od 40ak gigabajta sa podacima koje je uspio da ukrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;E sada, podaci su ukrani, kompanija Gamma koja stoji iza programa je odbila da komentariše da je neko provalio u njihov sistem, a baza je postala dostupna u javnosti. Sada je na redu onaj manje zabavan dio: analiziranje svih tih podataka. Zanima me da li će iko od domaćih medija biti spreman za to. Ja jesam, zato trenutno preuzimam torrent od svih 40ak gigabajta.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Međutim, ono što me navelo da se zapravo uputim u ovu pustolovinu jeste to što se među podacima koje su do sada analizirali neki od osoba koji su preuzeli torrent našle različite države kao naručioci ovog proizvoda. Osobe koje analiziraju te podatke su došle do imena država preko Gamminog sistema za podršku tako što su obraćali pažnju na osobe koje su jednostavno otkrile državu koju predstavljaju ne prateći pravila za anonimnost na internetu (tipa koristeći mejl sa .ba domenom ili slično). A, ono najzanimljivije za nas jeste što se među tim državama našla i Bosna i Hercegovina!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ko li špijunira iz našeg državnog vrha i koga to tačno? Ostaje nam da vidimo. Meni fali još nekih dan i 13 sati da preuzmem sve podatke (limitovao sam brzinu da ne ograničim previše korišćenje interneta drugim ukućanima) pa se bacam na analiziranje. Svakako ću sve što otkrijem objaviti na ovom blogu i na svom &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/r3bl_&quot;&gt;Tviter nalogu&lt;/a&gt;, pa pratite ako vas zanima.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Međutim, ono što me trenutno zanima više od same vijesti jeste to koliko će daleko dogurati vijest u našoj javnosti? Da li će se bilo koji portal ili medijska kuća uopšte obazirati na ovo? Da li će pokriti priču? Da li će iko osim mene pokušati da sazna koji se kurac zapravo događa i to pokušati da podijeli sa javnošću?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ostaje nam samo da čekamo i saznamo.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Back to Kubuntu</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/linux/2014/08/07/back-to-kubuntu/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-07T16:50:46+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/linux/2014/08/07/back-to-kubuntu</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, in the last 48 hours I was again, looking for a new distro. Don’t know why, but I just felt I should be using something else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And again, I was search for the perfect distro for my needs. As you know if you’re following my blog, I’m a big security researcher kind a guy. So, naturally, my first choice was Kali Linux. But, the problem is that I don’t like GNOME interface. Don’t know why, but it’s just not right for me. So, I tried compiling my own Kali Linux .iso file with KDE interface. Well, it’s easy to say that that didn’t work as planned. I did not manage to get it working. So I tried installing regular Kali Linux and replacing GNOME interface with KDE. That also didn not work as planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I felt kinda noobish. Even though I’ve tried a lot of distros and even though I did install Kali Linux before as my main operating system, I just could not get it to work perfectly with my Windows 8.1 and a TrueCrypt-encrypted shared partition. So I decided I should use some other KDE-based distro and fill it up with security software. I installed openSUSE but I just could not get their password manager. So I decided I should stick with Kubuntu because I wanted that apt-get so badly! It took me at least three or four clean installs to get it to work right. I kept changing my repo server that messed things up. Once I even stopped the upgrade command in progress and that messed things up for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, finally, I managed to get it to work. And it feels great and robust just as I hoped it will. So, I’m back with Kubuntu, I really like the job the Kubuntu developers are doing and I’m also considering about joining the community and participating in Kubuntu development. But first, a couple of days of trying it out, just to make sure I don’t mess anything up. Again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Papers We Love</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/2014/08/07/papers-we-love/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-07T01:07:46+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/2014/08/07/papers-we-love</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;If you’re like me, the chances are you like learning new things. If you’re like me, than you love computer science. I have a big passion to learn as much as I can about computers. Because it’s kind of a huge subject and no human could ever learn everything about computers, I had to decide which subject I should focus on. The choice was not that hard for me and I’ve decided relatively easy that my subject of choice is cyber security. I care about privacy and man do I love breaking things!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what I want to represent today is a git. Inside that git, you’ll find a lot of computer science related academic papers uploaded my people like you and me. The point of doing this git is to create a high quality source for papers, and those 50 contributors are doing the hell of a job doing that. It’s the little projects like this that makes me happy. When people unite and do something awesome together. I’m even happier because this is the first use of git I found useful that is not related to any programming language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you do have some spare time, some research papers stored on your local drive and a wish to give back to the community, I will ask you to visit &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/papers-we-love/papers-we-love&quot;&gt;Papers We Love repository&lt;/a&gt;, fork it and upload the shit out of good quality papers to it! I know I will. Especially because I saw that the security section is pretty empty for now.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Confession: Microsoft Is Not So Bad</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/2014/08/05/confession-microsoft-is-not-so-bad/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-05T14:02:03+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/2014/08/05/confession-microsoft-is-not-so-bad</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There’s something I need to confess. Even though I’m a hardcore Linux and free software advocate, I have to say that Microsoft, as a company, is not so bad. So, why am I saying this?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve never paid a single euro for any Microsoft product. I was running cracked software like 95% of people in my country. Now this is not a secret at all. My father runs a small company (around 10 of employees) and I was doing some research about how licensing works in my country. I was amazed. As it turns out, the companies &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; required to have licensed software, &lt;em&gt;but&lt;/em&gt;, if the inspection comes, they will look at a specific list of software and they’ll ask you if you have a license for those programs. What I’m trying to say is that a company only needs to have legal operating system, legal office suite and that’s about it. Add some Adobe products if you use them inside of your company and you’re good to go! Now, the situation gets even worse when we focus on personal users. No-one will &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; ask you for a license. It’s like this word doesn’t even exist in my country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, back to the story. So, I was running cracked Windows software until a year and a half. Then I found out about the world of Linux and I’ve never looked back. But, being a student and using nothing but open source technology is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard in a country like mine (and practically anywhere else in the world!). So, my first year began and they required more and more of proprietary software for us to have. Most of them are developed by Microsoft. But, we also got a DreamSpark account, so most of the software they required from us were free of charge. That’s how I got my Microsoft Visio, Microsoft Visual Studio and stuff like that, all for nothing. After that, number of unlicensed programs I had from Microsoft was down to two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I’ve said earlier in the story, my father is running a small company. After catastrophical floods that hit south-east part of Europe in this year, my father had to start his job all over. So what he did is he bought a new laptop for himself and he needed to buy Microsoft’s Office license. All they had in as store we looked up was a single license for Office 365 Home Plus. He decided to take it. What I’ve found out after that is that this license can be used by &lt;em&gt;five email addresses&lt;/em&gt; legally. He used the first one for his laptop, and I used the second for mine. Also got some extra space in OneDrive and some free premium Skype minutes. And now, I’m down to one, and it’s the main one: Microsoft’s Windows 8.1. Not sure how I will get the license for it, but I’m sure I somehow will. The license costs somewhere around 100 euros, which is about the same as the amount of money I spend on food, cigarettes and going out in a month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, while I was downloading Microsoft Visio from my DreamSpark account, I found out something else. I found out that I have a free license for Windows Store in my DreamSpark account. Oh, and also, I got an access to Microsoft Virtual Academy with _a lot _of courses and I got some books for free as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to summarize things up, I got a lot of software from Microsoft and I didn’t actually pay anything to use it. I got only a couple of software products without a license for now but I’m working on replacing them with something legal. And I’m still trying to find my Linux alternative to &lt;a href=&quot;http://elementaryos.org/&quot;&gt;elementary OS&lt;/a&gt;. While waiting for &lt;a href=&quot;http://isfreyareleasedyet.com/&quot;&gt;Freya&lt;/a&gt;, I’m spending most of my time in Windows looking for some alternative I will use until Freya is released. No luck for now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I trust Microsoft a lot more than I trust Google.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Sensitive Data Grabber Project</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///projects/2014/08/03/sensitive-data-grabber-project/"/>
   <updated>2014-08-03T15:18:43+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//projects/2014/08/03/sensitive-data-grabber-project</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, what I want to present to you today is a project I’m currently working on. What I’m doing is I’m creating a program that will collect all of the sensitive data from the victim’s computer and saves them on a thumb drive. The program is currently being written as a form application using Microsoft’s Visual Basic and .NET framework 4.5. After I finish the beta version, I’m planning on re-writing the program so it will be a console application and it will work with some older .NET framework (I’m not yet sure which .NET framework will I support for now).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, what I want to do is to tell you what this program actually does for now and what I’m planning on implementing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, the program will collect some basic data about victim’s computer. That data includes information like OS version, number of processors, RAM available, username in use, domain name, machine name and similar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, the program will check if you have installed applications that are currently supported. Here is the list:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Evernote&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google Chrome&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft OneNote&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mozilla Firefox&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mozilla Thunderbird&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pidgin&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Steam&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;World of Tanks&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next stop: copying some data! Here’s the list of applications and a current list of sensitive data it will copy:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Evernote – file containing victim’s current username, email associated with that username and a copy of victim’s current database (implementing it right now).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Google Chrome – files containing bookmarks, cookies, history, login data and web data.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Microsoft OneNote – the copy of all of the victim’s notebooks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mozilla Firefox – files containing cookies, addons, form history and downloads history.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Mozilla Thunderbird – files containing addons, address book and cookies (planning on supporting of copying all of the emails if a victim uses POP3 instead of IMAP).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pidgin – file containing all of the victim’s usernames and passwords in clear text and a directory where victim’s logs are saved.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Steam – configuration file containing a list of all users ever connected on that PC and some decryption keys (not sure what those are for, but I will find it out).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;World of Tanks – file containing all of your preferences and a folder containing your latest battle results.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, the program will automatically locate your removable drive and store all of those files in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of doing that program is to prove that a lot of pretty sensitive data is easily accessible to someone who has a physical access to your Windows machine. Combine those two and the victim gets pwned big time. The program is currently in pre-alpha stage and I don’t recommend anyone using it for now, but if anyone wants to look at the code for now, you can do that &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/aleksandar-todorovic/SensitiveDataGrabber&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Once it’s finished, it will be open source (licensed under GPL) and everyone will be able to add programs to the compatibility list.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Notes on Build Your Own Cyber Lab at Home Course</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/2014/07/28/notes-on-build-your-own-cyber-lab-at-home-course/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-28T15:18:17+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/2014/07/28/notes-on-build-your-own-cyber-lab-at-home-course</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Recently I finished a free course offered &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cybersecurityschoolonline.com/&quot;&gt;Cyber Security School Online&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href=&quot;http://udemy.com/&quot;&gt;Udemy&lt;/a&gt; called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.udemy.com/build-your-own-cyber-lab-at-home/#/&quot;&gt;Build Your Own Cyber Lab from Home&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I want to do now is to share the notes I’ve written while taking the course. The courses are divided into a couple of cathegories and they’re written for my current knowledge and situation, but I hope that there will be a person out there that will find them useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are the links to &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0By-yP9sfB84VTkhGX2g0N1VvLU0/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;.odt version&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://drive.google.com/file/d/0By-yP9sfB84VZHA5Zjg4X096Yms/edit?usp=sharing&quot;&gt;.pdf version&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>The Internet of Insecure Things</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/2014/07/27/the-internet-of-insecure-things/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-27T14:13:30+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/2014/07/27/the-internet-of-insecure-things</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, Internet of Things is happening. More and more things are connected to the internet every day. What about securing the Internet of Things? This great presentation by &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/securityweekly&quot;&gt;@securityweekly&lt;/a&gt; covered most of the problems. And I laughed a lot while reading it. Too bad I can’t listen to him explaining it in details.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;http://www.slideshare.net/pauldotcom/the-internet-of-insecure-things-10-most-wanted-list&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>How Hacking Changed My Life</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/linux/2014/07/27/how-hacking-changed-my-life/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-27T13:47:21+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/linux/2014/07/27/how-hacking-changed-my-life</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I already wrote about my hacking beginnings &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/07/12/flashback-my-first-cybersecurity-discovery/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/07/27/flashback-my-first-steps-in-hacking/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Now, I want to talk about something else. I want to talk about how hacking changed my life!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, first of all, because I kept running into BackTrack tutorials while I was learning how to hack, I began to be interested in Linux and free software. I’ve spent days trying to install BackTrack in a virtual machine and connecting it with my network. I thought I just couldn’t configure my VM but, at the time, I didn’t know that I need to enter some command in terminal to unblock WiFi in BackTrack which was blocked for some reason whenever I booted into live CD or just installed BackTrack on my computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I decided I’m tired of playing with VMs and for no obvious reason at all, I decided I should try to install it directly on my laptop. And I did manage to work it out! That was my first Linux distro I ever installed and it definitely wasn’t my last one (over the time I tried BackTrack, Linux Mint, Fedora, Arch Linux, elementary OS, Ubuntu, Kali Linux and wright now I’m running Kubuntu). Tinkering with free software is awesome and I contributed a lot to free software. So, hacking got me into free software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the beginning, I was really hooked up to Anonymous movement. I read this book called &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.amazon.com/We-Are-Anonymous-LulzSec-Insurgency/dp/0316213527&quot;&gt;We Are Anonymous: Inside the Hacker World of LulzSec, Anonymous, and the Global Cyber Insurgency&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; and I was instantly hooked. So I started following Anonymous community in Facebook, YouTube, Twitter and I’ve seen numerous times that they posted pictures where they say reading is better than watching TV. They’ve kinda changed the way I look at the world. Following them was the reason I started reading books actively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of hacking, I learned a lot about computers. I did spend my whole summer learning as much as I can but now I’m confident that I’m in the top twenty persons in my local community in knowledge about computers and networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hacking woke up my thirst for knowledge, my thirst for books, and it kinda changed my view of the world through Anonymous. I’m not impressed with Anonymous as I used to be, but they did learn me a lot of things.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hacking is awesome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P.S. &lt;a href=&quot;https://aleksandartodorovic.wordpress.com/2014/07/27/blogilo-wordpress-integration-is-terrible/&quot;&gt;QTM is great&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Blogilo + Wordpress integration is terrible!</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/2014/07/27/blogilo-wordpress-integration-is-terrible/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-27T13:14:52+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/2014/07/27/blogilo-wordpress-integration-is-terrible</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;First of all, sorry about the design of my previous post. I was trying Blogilo as a program for posting entries and the result was horrible! What I did is write down a post in LO Writer (need spelling while I write), copied it to Blogilo and clicked submit. The font was terrible, and I had to edit a post from a web interface because somewhere between my Blogilo and my blog some spaces just disappered!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, now I’m writing in QTM and I hope the post will be formated better before I write my next post in it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Flashback: My First Steps in Hacking</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/2014/07/27/flashback-my-first-steps-in-hacking/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-27T12:48:26+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/2014/07/27/flashback-my-first-steps-in-hacking</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was always a curious guy. I was always wondering how do some things work, but I just didn’t know how to find out about it. I, at the time, followed Discovery Channel, Viasat Explorer and other scientific shows because I wanted to know more. I would write down everything I thought it was fun to learn in my little notebook as a reference if I needed to learn more about that. I didn’t prepare for doing something like that. That’s why my notes were messy and Icouldn’t do anything about it. And of course, at the time, I did not have a computer or internet or smartphone or anything like that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So,years later, I finally got internet connection! I was 16 years old back then. Yup, I lived 16 years without the internet and I can’t be happier about it. I had a nice childhood. Anyway, when I finally got an access to the internet, I did spend two years doing nothing and exploring the power of internet. I used Facebook a lot, used Skype, YouTube, and basically got an account in every social site ever. I was senior in high-school when I learned a thing or two about computers. I already mastered Pascal and Delphi, I knew some networking basics and I knew a lot about building my own desktop computer. But in my senior year, I was learning object-oriented programming. And while I was learning Visual Basic (6.0 was theversion my school decided to teach), I needed to do my final exam using Visual Basic, some basic printing app that will connect to MySQL database my friend was doing and print stuff from it on a specifically designed pieces of paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I didn’t want to do it Visual Basic 6.0. That version was sooo old! And I needed some support looking things up on the internet! So I decided I should download Visual Studio 2012. And I did. And I learned programming in Visual Basic that’s four or five versions more advanced than the version they taught us in school. I felt so proud!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, I didn’t manage to finish the whole final exam. The app was full of bugs and I didn’t like it. While I was presenting my final work to a couple my teachers I managed to socially engineer them (at the time, I had no idea what social engineering is exactly, but stillmanaged to pull it off) and I got the highest grade &lt;em&gt;without everactually running my program&lt;/em&gt;! Damn that felt so good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, my high-school was finished and I had some spare months until my collage begins. I started being curious. I wanted to know what that &lt;em&gt;s _represents in _https&lt;/em&gt;. So I started learning, and learning. I did DDoS a couple of websites, did some automated SQL injection using Havij accessed some admin panels using passwords I extracted using Havij and that was pretty much the whole scope of my hacking back then.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Time to take some break</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/2014/07/26/time-to-take-some-break/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-26T13:04:16+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/2014/07/26/time-to-take-some-break</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Time to take a few days break from learning because I got a hold of a next book in A Song of Ice and Fire series I love so much: A Clash of Kings. I’m a huge Game of Thrones fan and I like books even more!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>[NinjaSec Course] Gathering Information</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///cyber%20security/2014/07/24/ninjasec-course-gathering-information/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-24T14:53:38+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//cyber%20security/2014/07/24/ninjasec-course-gathering-information</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I know that this post is going to be pretty basic, but it was not very detailed in my head so I wanted to write about it to remember it easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what tools and techniques can someone use to gather information about a certain person or company?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, your best friend is Google + Evernote combination. Basically, what you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; do is to write down all of the data you think it will be usable in Evernote. Next, look up that company using social sites such as Facebook, Twitter, LinkedIn etc. now, why is that important? Well, it is important because maybe their employees listed that company as their job on their social sites. From there, you can find out a lot about who is working there. Write it down in Evernote and proceed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next stop is finding out what their workers do the best. So you’ll use maybe a little social engineering to get to information their employees are posting on their social media. By looking at their resumes, their likes and their tweets, you can find out a lot about a certain person. After you do that, you just match them up to see where do their interests combine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For an example, if a couple of their employees listed Java as their field of expertize on their LinkedIn profile, there’s a big chance that their site or applications they provide will include some parts of Java code. Your job is to find more that clues and to paint as precise picture of a company as possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does not seem that hard, does it?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>[NinjaSec Course] Organizing information during PenTest</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///cyber%20security/2014/07/24/ninjasec-course-organizing-information-during-pentest/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-24T10:10:58+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//cyber%20security/2014/07/24/ninjasec-course-organizing-information-during-pentest</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, I found about this great tool for organizing notes while you do the penetration testing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s basically a simple note-taking app called &lt;a href=&quot;http://dradisframework.org/download.html&quot;&gt;Dradis&lt;/a&gt; specifically designed to be used in penetration testing purposes. It’s open source, written in Ruby and runs straight in your browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything you write down for a project will be password encrypted and stored in a SQLite database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does not have text formatting option, so you can’t really rely on your notes to look pretty, but it has an option of importing data from some of the most known intelligence gathering applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although I was impressed that there is a tool specifically designed for using for penetration testing purposes, it’s not something I will be using. Although I’m actively searching for a good &lt;a href=&quot;https://evernote.com/&quot;&gt;Evernote&lt;/a&gt; alternative (I do not feel comfortable storing my notes on their server and I’m not comfortable that my notes are not encrypted on my hard drive), I got kinda used to using it, so I will be using Evernote at least for a while, while I’m still trying to find some good alternative that has my privacy as their main goal, but can also sync my notes on both of my systems (Windows 8.1 and elementary OS of course).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Starting an Ethical Hacking Course</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/2014/07/23/starting-an-ethical-hacking-course/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-23T22:50:58+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/2014/07/23/starting-an-ethical-hacking-course</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, I found out about a personal blog about network security and while reading it I found out about a course offered by Udemy learning platform called: &lt;em&gt;Learn the Basics of Ethical Hacking and Penetration Testing&lt;/em&gt;. I used Google to find out if there is some code to finish that course for free and, of course, I managed to find it (thank you Reddit!). So, from now on I will probably write on my blog some information about how well am I doing in that course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, I’m planning on writing a really long essay about the true type of hackers, who they are and what they do. My point of writing that essay is to try to convince people in my local area to think differently about a word &lt;em&gt;hacker&lt;/em&gt; next time they read it on some news reporting sites. The essay will be written in my native language (Bosnian) for one reason only and that is because I know that I’m not excellent with grammar in English language and I don’t want my essay to be full of grammatical errors.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Laverna</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/2014/07/20/laverna/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-20T05:07:04+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/2014/07/20/laverna</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I found out about a great note-taking web-app called &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Laverna/laverna&quot;&gt;Laverna&lt;/a&gt;. It’s an open source program that you can just download on your PC and run through your browser*. It has a built-in AES encryption so you can store confidential data in it. All your data will be encrypted using you password. It also supports saving your database in the cloud (via Dropbox or via SecureStorage with more cloud services to be implemented soon).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I need to say that even though its list of features is pretty amazing, the web-app has a lot of bugs. If you encounter some of them, I highly suggest that you report them &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Laverna/laverna/issues&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This seems like a fun and simple project. I’m probably going to write about Evernote and OneNote open source alternatives in a new edition of &lt;a href=&quot;http://libre.lugons.org/&quot;&gt;LiBRE! Magazine&lt;/a&gt; so be sure to keep an eye on our site if you speak Serbian/Bosnian/Croatian language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I noticed that the application does not support Internet Explorer 11.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Man, Networking is Hard!</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/2014/07/12/man-networking-is-hard/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-12T15:06:57+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/2014/07/12/man-networking-is-hard</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, I started my college education last October. First semester I wasn’t very good. I passed tree of five subjects I was supposed to pass and I got pretty much amazing grades in the subjects I did pass. But now, during the second semester, I started learning for my Cisco CCNA certificate. That certificate was the reason I decided to go on this collage (although, to be honest, my choice was very limited considering my financial situation at the time).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, I came to the end of the second semester. In my R&amp;amp;S course (first course in the path to CCNA certificate), I wasn’t very active. I didn’t go to all of the classes in that course I wasn’t very regular in lab exercises. I did not study every week and I had more and more materials to learn. I knew that, but I just didn’t pay attention. I took collage for granted and now I have a problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomorrow is my final test in my R&amp;amp;S course and I’m stuck. I did &lt;em&gt;try&lt;/em&gt; to study for it as much as I could in the last ten days. I managed to learn first eight chapters, but I got stuck during the chapter nine. I just can’t understand subnetting and it’s just a big pain in the butt for me. I lost my concentration and now I have no idea what to do. I studied that chapter yesterday. I’ve spent pretty much all of my day studying it and I still couldn’t finish a basic subnetting in Packet Tracer. Now, I’m trying to do the same, but I just cannot concentrate at all. And, I still have two more chapter to go through after I finish this one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Passing this exam is not going to be easy at all, but I will give my best. After all, being a cybersecurity specialist is my dream for a couple of years, and I just can’t be that if I don’t understand how networks actually work. This is going to be a long night.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Flashback: My first cybersecurity “discovery”</title>
   <link href="http://r3bl.github.io///about%20me/cyber%20security/human%20hacking/2014/07/12/flashback-my-first-cybersecurity-discovery/"/>
   <updated>2014-07-12T14:31:36+02:00</updated>
   <id>http://r3bl.github.io//about%20me/cyber%20security/human%20hacking/2014/07/12/flashback-my-first-cybersecurity-discovery</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So, when I was 12 years old (at least I think I was) I didn’t have a functioning computer. My father contacted one of my neighbor and he had a spare laptop he didn’t use for a long time. He gave it to my family and I finally had something to amuse me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The year was 2006. I was living in a small village located in northern Bosnia &amp;amp; Herzegovina, 40 kilometers away from the nearest town. Not an ideal place to live, I know. Having an internet in a place like that in that age was a privilege that not a lot of people could afford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I had a laptop that was previously used, no internet connection and not a lot of games. The laptop had Windows 98 installed. Unlike my family, that neighbor that gave us that laptop had an internet access. So, I started tinkering with it to see what’s in there. I accessed system folder in that thing and after a few days I noticed a directory that sounded fun: Temporary Internet Files. That sounded like fun. I had no idea what was stored in there but I wanted to find out. So I opened a directory. It had numerous amount of subdirectories and some picture files. Hm, I wonder what kind of images were there. And then, I made my first cybersecurity discovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That directory was packed with porn pictures. Literally hundreds of them. I haven’t used such an old Windows system since then, but I guess my neighbor used Internet Explorer and I guess that Internet Explorer kept all of temporary pictures inside that folder back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time, I was really into command prompt. I didn’t know what it does and I didn’t know any commands on it, but I wanted to find out how to use it. So I started typing some random commands and once I typed in: help. That command gave me a list of all available cmd commands so I started to tinker with my laptop. I managed to do some basic changes to the system using cmd. I changed the time and date of the system and I couldn’t be more proud of me than I was back then.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, to combine these two stories. I knew about that Temporary Internet Files folder and I didn’t know pretty much anything about cmd and what it does. I remember once I opened up my cmd, pressed Ctrl+Enter (keyboard shortcut that opened cmd in full screen back then). So I started typing this long text as a command. That text included my opinion about that neighbor after I discovered that directory. Yeah, you could only imagine what a 12 year old boy would think about some friend of his father after he discovered that. So I typed it and at the end I wrote a sentence that basically said: If you ever read this, stay away from John Doe! And I pressed enter. The command did nothing of course, it was just some plain text written in my native language. I know, what a dumb thing to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, I never looked at that neighbor the same after that of course. I felt like a detective that found out something valuable. I remember coming to their house one day with my family, playing with his daughters, and looking for a chance to somehow get in his bedroom unnoticed so I could find out more. Yeah, I thought he was a freaking child molester or something. In the end, I didn’t get the chance to get to his bedroom unnoticed, so I gave up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that, that laptop got some hardware problems and it eventually stopped working. My detective story has ended there. But, six or seven years later, I started studying more about computer networks so I could protect people like my poor neighbor who just wanted to watch some porn videos unnoticed. And so, my journey into cybersecurity field has begun.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
